<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anno primo &amp; secundo Philippi &amp; Mariæ actes made at a Parliament, begon and holde[n] at Westminster, the xij. daye of Nouember, in the fyrste and seconde yeare of the reigne of our soueraygne lorde and lady Philip and Mary, by the grace of God, Kinge &amp; Quene of England, Fraunce, Naples, Jerusalem, and Ireland, defendours of the fayth, princes of Spayne and Cycilie, archedukes of Austria, dukes of Myllayn, Burgondie, and Braband, counties of Haspurge, Flau[n]ders and Tyroll, and there continued and kept to the dissolution of the same, beynge the xvi. day of Januarye then next ensuynge, were enacted as foloweth.</title>
            <title>Laws, etc.</title>
            <author>England and Wales.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1555</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 204 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A22992</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 9447.9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1983</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22960512</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22960512</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25971</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A22992)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25971)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1793:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anno primo &amp; secundo Philippi &amp; Mariæ actes made at a Parliament, begon and holde[n] at Westminster, the xij. daye of Nouember, in the fyrste and seconde yeare of the reigne of our soueraygne lorde and lady Philip and Mary, by the grace of God, Kinge &amp; Quene of England, Fraunce, Naples, Jerusalem, and Ireland, defendours of the fayth, princes of Spayne and Cycilie, archedukes of Austria, dukes of Myllayn, Burgondie, and Braband, counties of Haspurge, Flau[n]ders and Tyroll, and there continued and kept to the dissolution of the same, beynge the xvi. day of Januarye then next ensuynge, were enacted as foloweth.</title>
                  <title>Laws, etc.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1553-1558 : Mary I)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>xxxiiii [i.e. 68] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In ædibus Iohannis Cawodi tipographi regiæ maiestatis,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Excusum Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno MDLV [1555]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>"Cum priuilegio Regiæ Maiestatis."</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁶ B⁴ C-F⁶.</note>
                  <note>Title within illustrated border.</note>
                  <note>Pages numbered on recto only.</note>
                  <note>Numerous errors in paging.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Law --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="engraved_title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25971:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25971:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figure>
                     <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                     <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anno Primo &amp; ſecundo Philippi &amp; Mariae.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ACTES</hi> made at a Parliament, begon and holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Weſtminſter, the .xij. daye of Nouember, in the fyrſte and ſeconde yeare of the reigne of our ſoueraygne Lorde, and Lady Philip and Mary, by the grace of God, kinge &amp; Quene of England, Fraunce, Naples, Ieruſalem, and Ireland, defendours of the fayth, Princes of Spayne and Cycilie, Archedukes of Auſtria, dukes of Myllayn, Burgondie, and Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, counties of Haſpurge, Flau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Tyroll, and there conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued and kept to the diſſolution of the ſame, beynge the .xvi. day of Ianuarye then next enſuynge, were enacted as foloweth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cum priuilegio Regiae Maiestatis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figDesc>engraved title page</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:25971:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N act touchyng letters patentes, and other writynges to be ſygned by the quenes Maieſtie. Ca. i.</item>
               <item>An act for the reformation of exceſſe in apparel. Cap. ii.</item>
               <item>An act againſt ſeditious wordes and rumours. cap. iii.</item>
               <item>An act for the puniſhment of certayne perſons callinge themſelues Egiptians. Cap. iiii.</item>
               <item>An acte to reſtrayne caryinge of corne, victuals, and woode, ouer the Sea. Cap. v.</item>
               <item>An act for the reuiuynge of three eſtatutes, made the punyſhement of hereſyes. Cap. vi.</item>
               <item>An act that perſons dwellyng in the countrey ſhall not ſell dyuers wares in cytyes and Townes corporate by retayle. Cap. vii.</item>
               <item>An act repealing al ſtatutes, articles, and prouiſions, made agaynſt the ſea apoſtolyke of Rome, ſynce the twenty yeare of kynge Henry theyght, and alſo for the eſtabliſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of al ſpiritual, &amp; eccleſiaſtical poſſeſſions, and hereditamentes conueyed to the laytye. Cap. viii.</item>
               <item>An act for the puniſhment of trayterous words agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quenes maieſty. Cap. ix.</item>
               <item>An act wherby certayne offences be made treaſons, and alſo for the gouernement of the kynges and Quenes Maieſtyes iſſue. Cap. x.</item>
               <item>An act for the puniſhment of bryngynge in of counterfeyt coyne of forreyne realmes, being curraunte within this realme, Cap. xi.</item>
               <item>An acte touching the impoundyng of diſtreſſes. Cap. xii.</item>
               <item>An act appoyntyng in order to Iuſtyces of peace, touchyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of pryſoners. Cap, xiii.</item>
               <item>An act for the makyng of ruſſels ſatens, ſattens reuerſes, and fuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an of Naples in Norwyche. Cap. xiiii.</item>
               <item>An acte to confirme the liberties of the lord Marchers in Wales. Cap. xv.</item>
               <item>An act for the continuaunce of certayne ſtatutes. Cap. xvi.</item>
               <item>An act touching leaſes hereafter to be made by certayne ſpirituall perſons. Cap. xvii.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="ii" facs="tcp:25971:2"/>
            <head>¶An act touchynge letters patentes and other writinges, to be ſigned by the Quenes maieſtie.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The fyrſt Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in the Parlymente begonne and holden at Weſtminſter, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde day of Apryl in the fyrſt yere of the reygne of our mooſte dreade and gracious Soueraygne Ladye the Queenes maieſtye, and there co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued &amp; kept til y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame being the fift day of May, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> next folowing, one acte was made touchinge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> articles of her highnes moſt noble mariage. In y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> which act amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt other thinges it was ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, ordred, &amp; eſtabliſhed by thauctority of the ſaid parliament, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all and ſinguler giftes, grauntes, letters patentes, exchanges, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, leaſes, and other writinges, which after the ſayd mariage and during the ſame ſhould paſſe, and be made of any benefices, offi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, landes, reuenues, and fruites, or of any of them, ſhould be intite<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led and made in the names of our Soueraigne Lord the king, and of her moſt excellent highnes, whether his Maieſty ſhould be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent within the realmes and dominions of her highnes, or w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in any of them, or abſent. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that the ſame giftes, grantes, letters paten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, eſchanges, confirmations, leaſes, and other writynges, ſo ſette forth and made, ſhould be ſealed, and firmed with the ſigne manuel of her highnes, and the ſame ſo ſigned &amp; ſealed with the great ſeale of this realme or w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch ſeale as hath bene accuſtomed, ſhould be by thauctoritie of the ſaid parliament, demed, adiudged, declared, and pronounced, to be as good perfect, and of like force, ſtrength, &amp; effect in the lawe, to al intentes, conſtructions, and purpoſes, againſt our ſayd Soueraigne Lord and Lady, the king and the Queenes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtyes, and her highnes heires and ſucceſſours, as yf her maieſtye had bene at the tyme of the making therof, ſole and vnmaried, and that al giftes, grauntes, letters patentes, eſchaunges, confirmatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s leaſes, and other writinges, which after the ſayde mariage, and during the time of the ſame, ſhould paſſe and be made of the ſaid be nefices, offices, landes, reuenues, and fruites, or of any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wher vnto the ſigne manuell, of her highnes, ſhoulde not be ſette made, or put, ſhalbe by thaucthoritye of the ſayde parliament, from to tyme, demed, adiudged, accepted, taken, and decreed, to be of no force, ne ef<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fect, but vtterly fruſtrate and boyde in the lawe, to all ententes, con
<pb facs="tcp:25971:3"/>
ſtructions and purpoſes, the ſayd mariage or any law, vſage, or cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, to the contrary in any wiſe not withſtanding, as by the ſayde act more at large doth appeare.</p>
               <p>Sithence the making of which Statute, and the ſolemniſation of the ſayd mariage the queenes moſt excellent maieſtye hath bene greatly moleſted, greued, and troubled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſigning of letters pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tentes, giftes, grauntes, eſchaunges, leaſes, and other writynges, concerning and touchinge benefices, offices, landes, reuenues, and fruites, made and graunted by, and from our ſayd ſoueraygne lord the kynge and her highnes, to ſundrye of their moſt louynge ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, to whome alſo it hath bene, and is, no ſmal charge to atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyl ſuch tyme as they may procure and obteyne the ſigne manuel of her highnes, vnto their ſayd letters patentes, giftes, grauntes, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunges, confirmations, and leaſes, without which ſigne the ſame are vtterly voyde by force of the ſayd ſtatute, to the great dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, loſſe, and vtter vndoing of diuers perſons, that haue lately bought purchaſed or obtayned of our ſayd ſoueraigne Lord and Lady, the kyng and Quenes maieſties, diuers landes, tenementes, and other hereditamentes to their great coſtes and charges.</p>
               <p>For remedy wherof be it enacted by the auctoritie of this preſent parliament, that the ſayde braunche or article touchinge or concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng only the ſigning of letters patentes, giftes, grauntes, eſchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, confirmations leaſes, or of other writynges, for any landes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices, offices, reuenues, fruites, or other hereditamentes, ſhall be from henceforth clearely repelled, and made fruſtrate, and voyde, to al intentes and purpoſes.</p>
               <p>And be it further enacted by auctoritie of this preſent parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that al and ſinguler letters patentes, touching or concernyng anye gift, grannte, eſchaunge, confirmation, leaſe, or other writynge, the whiche ſithence the ſayde mariage hath paſſed, and be made of any benefices, offices, manours, landes, tenementes, renenus, fruites, liberties, or other hereditamentes, or of anye of them in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> names of our moſt dread Soueraygne Lorde and Ladye, the kynge and the Quenes maieſties (the waraunt or writyng, or warauntes or wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynges wherof being ſigned with her highnes ſigne manuel in ſuch fourme order and degre, as the ſame heretofore haue bene accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be ſigned, when her high nes was ſole and vnmaryed) ſhalbe by auctoritie of this preſent parliament of the ſame like force, ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gth and effecte in the lawe, to al intentes, conſtructions, and purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as yf the ſame were or had bene ſigned by her highnes ſigne ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nuel, and as yf her maieſtie had bene at the tyme of the making ther of, ſole and vnmaryed, and as they were before the makynge of the ſayd act. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayde eſtatute, or any braunche, or article therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned to the contrary in any wyſe notwythſtandynge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:25971:3"/>
               <head>¶ An act for the reformation of exceſſe in apparel. ¶ The ſeconde Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>E it enacted by thauctoritie of thys preſent Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that no perſon borne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in this realme, or the dominions of the ſame, other then the ſon &amp; heyre apparaunt of a knight, or other then ſuche, as maye diſpend .xx.li. by the yere in landes, offices, fees, or other yerely reuenues for terme of lyfe, or be worth in goodes .ii. C. li. ſhall after the fyrſte daye of Apryll nexte com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng, weare any maner of ſylke in, or vpon hys hatte, bonet, night cappe, gyrdle, ſcabberde, hoſe, ſhoes or ſpurre leathers, vpon payne of thre monethes impryſonment, and forfeytures of .x.li. for euerye dayes wearyng contrary to the tenour of this act.</p>
               <p>And be it further enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayd, that Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of Aſſiſes, in theyr circuities, Iuſtices of peace in their ſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſheriffes in their turnes, Stewardes in letes &amp; lawe dayes, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iors, ſhieriffes, and Baylyffes of cities Boroughes, &amp; townes, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate in their courtes, ſhall, and may enquire, here and determine from time to time, al &amp; euery the ſayd offences, committed, or done wythin the lymites of theyr ſeuerall iuriſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and aucthorities, and where any ſuch forfeytures ſhal happen to be founde within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> precincte of any citie, bourough, towne corporate, lete or lawe day, then the Maior, ſherife, &amp; Baylyffes of the ſayde cities, boroughes, and townes, and owner of the ſayd lete or lawe dayes, to haue the one moytie of the ſayd forfeytures, and thother moytie to be to any ſubiecte of this realme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wil ſue for the ſame in any court of record by action information, byll, or otherwiſe, in which no wager of lawe protection, or aſſoigne ſhalbe allowed. And where ſuche for feyture ſhalbe found oute of any citie, boroughe, towne, lete, or lawe daye that the moytie of al ſuch forfeytures, ſhalbe to the kyng &amp; Quenes maieſties, and the heyres of the Quene, &amp; thother moytie there of to any of theyr ſubiectes, that wyl ſue for the ſame by byl, pl aint, ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, informatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or otherwiſe in any court of record as is aforeſaid, in which no wager of lawe, protection, or eſſoygne, ſhalbe admitted or allowed. And that al &amp; euery ſuch perſon &amp; perſons, as haue auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory tye by vertue of thys act, to heare &amp; determine the premyſſes may vpon the conuiction of euery ſuch offender award proces vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſhyrefe of anye ſhyre within thys realme, for the apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſayd offender, which beinge apprehended, ſhalbe commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the ſhyrefe vnto the gaole of the ſayd ſhyre, there to remayne without bayle or maynpriſe vntyl the ſayde offendoure hath payde the forfeyture wherin he is ſo conuicted.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25971:4"/>
And be it further enacted by the aucthorytye aforeſayde, that yf any perſon or perſons of what eſtate condition or degre ſoener he or they he, after y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſayd firſt day of Aprill next co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, knowing any ſeruaunt or ſeruauntes of his or theirs to offend contrary to this act, doo not put the ſame out of his or theyr ſeruice, but ſhall kepe in hys or their ſeruice the ſame offendour of offendors by the ſpace of xiiii. dayes next after ſuch knowledge had, or els beyng ſo put out of his theyr ſeruice ſhall retayne the ſame offendour or offendours to his or their ſeruyce agayne within one yere next enſuing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of committyng of any ſuch offence, the ſame perſon or perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſo ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping or reteyning agayne in or to his or their ſeruice, any ſuch ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt or ſeruauntes offending contrary to the tenour of this acte as is aforeſayd, ſhal for euery hys or theyr offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce forfeyt .c. li. of law full money of England, the moytye whereof to be to the kynge and Quenes maieſties vſe, and the heires and ſucceſſors of the Quene and the other moyte to hym that wyl ſue for the ſame in any courte of record, by action byl plaint information or otherwyſe, wherin no wager of law eſſoygne or protection ſhalbe admitted or allowed.</p>
               <p>Prouyded alwaye and be it enacted that thys acte, or anye thing therin conteyned, ſhal not extende to any perſon beyng of, or aboue the degre of a knyghtes ſonne or doughter, or beinge wife to any of them, nor to ſuch as haue bene be, or ſhalbe Maiour, Baylife Alderma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or head officer in any city, borough, or town corporate, or to the wife of any of them, nor to any of the kynges or Quenes ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes in ordinary wages attendaunt, &amp; wearyng the kynges or Quenes ordinary liueries, but that they &amp; euerye of them, may vſe and weare as they or any of them might lawfully vſe and weare be fore the makyng of thys act.</p>
               <p>Prouided alſo that no perſon ſhalbe compelled by thys acte, to put away his prentiſe or hyred ſeruaunte before thende of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> terme before agreed betwene the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor that any mayſter ſhal forfeyt or loſe any payne or forfeyture for the keping of his pre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiſe or hyred ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t after his offence, contrary to thys acte, vnto thend of the terme be fore agreed betwene them. Any thyng aboue ſayd to the contraay notwythſtandynge.</p>
               <p>Prouyded alſo, that women may weare in theyr cappes, hattes, gyrdles, and hoodes, as they or any of them myght vſe and weare lawfully before the makyng of thys acte.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ An Acte agaynſt ſeditious wordes and rumors. The thyrd Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="iiii" facs="tcp:25971:4"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here it is conteyned as well in the Statute of Weſtm. the firſte, as in the Statute made at Gloceſter the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde yere of the raygne of kynge Rychard the ſecond, that no man ſhoulde be ſo hardye to contriue, ſpeake, or tell any falſe newes, lyes, or other ſuche lyke falſe thynges of Prelates, Dukes, Earles, Barous, and other Nobles and Peares of the realme, or of the Chaunceloure, Treaſurer, Clerke of the priuie ſeale, Stewarde of the kynges houſholde, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of the one bancke or of thother, or of any of the great officers of this realme. And that euery ſuch offender ſhould be taken &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, vntil ſuch time as he had brought him or the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forth which did ſpeake the ſame. And wher alſo at a parliament holden at Cam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bridge in the .xii. yeare of the reygne of the ſayd kyng Rycharde, it was alſo enacted, that where anye ſuche offender as is aforeſayde ſhould be taken and impriſoned, and coulde not find him of whome he heard thoſe newes which he ſpake, as is aforeſaid, that then the ſame ſpeaker ſhould be puniſhed by thaduiſe of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell, as by the ſame actes amongeſt other more playnly do and may appeare.</p>
               <p>Be it enacted by thauctoritye of thys preſente parliament, that all and euery the ſayde former actes and Statutes ſhalbe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne in their ful force ſtrength and effecte, toal intentes, conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and purpoſes. And further that Iuſtices of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peace in euery Shire, citie, &amp; towne corporate, within the limittes of their ſeueral commiſſions, ſhal by auctoritye of thys preſent act, haue ful power to examine, heare and determine the cauſes aboue ſayd, in the ſayd two firſt actes ſpecified, and to put the ſayde two fyrſt ſtatutes and euery braunche in them conteyned in due execution that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth condigne puniſhement be not deferred from ſuche offenders.</p>
               <p>And for aſmuch as diuers and ſundrye malicious &amp; euyl dyſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed perſons maliciouſly, ſediciouſly, rebelliouſly, and vnnaturallye contrary to the duety of their fidelityes and allegiau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces haue now of late not only ymagined, inuented, practiſed, ſpoken and ſpredde abrode diuers and ſundry falſe, ſeditious &amp; ſclaunderous newes ru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mors, ſayinges, and tales agaynſt our mooſt dreade Soueraygne Lord and kyng, and agaynſt our mooſt naturall Soueraygne La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye and Quene, and agaynſt eyther of them, of whome we are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to thinke euyl, and much more to ſpeake euyl, which offence ſoundeth and is aſwel to the greate diſhoner reproche and ſclaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of their moſt excellent maieſties, as alſo to the great ſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der of this their realme, and other their dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, but alſo haue deuiſed, made written printed publiſhed and ſet forth diuers he ynous, ſedi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cious and ſclaunderous writinges rimes ballades letters papers and bokes, intending and practiſyng therby to moue and ſtyrre ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s diſcorde diſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion &amp; rebellion within this realme, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greate
<pb facs="tcp:25971:5"/>
peryll and daunger of the ſame.</p>
               <p>For auoydynge wherof, be it enacted by thauctoritie of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parliament, that yf any perſon or perſons, after the .xx. day of February next enſuing, and after open Proclamacion made of this Acte, ſhal maliciouſly, of his or theyr ymagination, ſpeake anye falſe ſedicious, &amp; ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derous newes, rumors ſayings, or tales of our ſaid Soueraigne Lord &amp; king, or of our ſaid moſt natural Soueraigne Lady &amp; Quene, that then al &amp; euery ſuch perſon &amp; perſones ſo offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding, beinge therof co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uicted or attainted, in forme hereafter, in this Acte expreſſed, ſhal for euerye fyrſt offence, in ſome markette place within the ſhyre, Citie or Borough, where, or neare vnto the place, where the ſaid wordes were, or ſhalbe ſo ſpoken, be ſet openly vpon the pilory, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sheriffe or his miniſters, if it ſhal fortune to be with out any citie or towne corporate. And if it happen to be with in ſuch cite or towne corporate, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> principal officer or officers of ſuch citie or towne corporate, or his or theyre miniſters, &amp; there to haue bothe his eares cute of, onleſſe he paye one hundreth poundes to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> King and Quenes highnes vſe within one moneth next after iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment geuen of his ſayd offence, and alſo ſhal ſuffer impriſonment by the ſpace of three monethes after ſuch his or theyr execution.</p>
               <p>And it is likewyſe enacted by thaucroritye aforeſayd, that al, and euery perſon &amp; perſons, whych after the ſayde day, and after Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation made of thys act, ſhal maliciouſly ſpeake any falſe ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſlaunderous newes, rumors, or tales to the ſlaunder and reproche of our ſayde Soueraygne lord the kynge, or of our ſayde moſt natural Soueraygne ladye the Queene, of the ſpeakynge or reportyng of any other, that then all, and euery ſuch perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſo ſpeaking and reportyng, being therof conuict or atteynted, in forme hereafter in thys act expreſſed, ſhall for euery ſuch offence in ſome market place within the ſhyre, citie, borough, or town, wher or nere vnto the place where the ſayd wordes were or ſhalbe ſo ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken &amp; reported, be ſet ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pillory by the ſhyref or his mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, if it ſhal fortune to be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out anye citie or towne corporat. And yf it ſhal happen to be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in any city or towne corporate, then by the principal offycer or offycers of ſuch city or towne corporat, or his or their miniſters, &amp; ther to haue one of hys eares cut of, onles he pay one .C. markes to the kynges and Queenes hyghnes vſe, wythin one moneth next after iudgement geuen of hys ſayde offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; alſo ſhall ſuffer impryſonmente by the ſpace of one moneth after hys or theyr execution.</p>
               <p>And be it further enacted by thauctoritye aforeſayd, that if any perſon or perſons ſhall after the ſayd day, and after Proclamation made as is aforeſayd, maliciouſly deuiſe, writ, print, or ſet forth any maner of boke time, ballade, letter, or writinge, conteynynge anye
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:25971:5"/>
falſe matter, clauſe, or ſentence of ſclaunder, reproche, and diſhonor of the kyng &amp; quenes maieſties, or of eyther of them, or to the encou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raging, ſturring or mouing of any inſurrection or rebellion, wythin this realme, or any dominions belongyng to the ſame. Or whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhall maliciouſlye procure, any ſuch booke, rime, ballade, letter, or writyng, written, prynted, or ſet furth, (and the ſayde offence not being puniſhable by the Statute, made in the .xxvi. yere of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reigne of king Edward the third, concerning treaſons, or declaratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon) that then and in euery ſuch caſe the offender and offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders ther in after his or their conuiction or attaynder, ſhal for his or their firſt offence, in ſome market place within the ſhyre, city, or borow, where the ſayd offence is, or ſhalbe committed or done, by the ſhirefe or his miniſters, yf it ſhal fortune to be without anye citie or towne corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and yf within ſuch citie or towne corporate, then by the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall officer, or officers of ſuche citye or towne corporate or by his or their miniſters, haue hys and their right hand ſtrycken of.</p>
               <p>And be it further enacted by thauctoritie aſoreſayd, that yf anye perſon or perſons, being once lawfully conuicted of any of thoffe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces aforeſayd, now prouided to be puniſhed by the execution of loſſes of eare, eares, or hand, as is aforeſayd, do afterwards eftſones offend in any of the offences aforeſayde, that then he or they ſo offendynge ſhal ſuffer impriſonment duryng hys or theyr lyues, wythout baile or maynpriſe, &amp; forfeyte and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſe to the kyng and quenes maieſtyes al hys and their goodes and cattels.</p>
               <p>And be it alſo enacted by thauctority aforeſayd, that al Iuſtices of oyer &amp; determiner, within the limittes of their commiſſion Iuſtices of aſſiſe in their ſeueral circuites, Iuſtices of gaole delyuerye, &amp; Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyces of peace, aſwel within the liberties as without, within the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittes of their ſeueral co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſions, in their generall ſeſſions, or other ſeſſions, which they or two of them wherof one of them to be of the <hi>Quorum,</hi> may and ſhall appoynt at theyr pleaſure, where and when nede ſhal require &amp; ſhal by vertue hereof, haue ful power and aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to enquire, here and determine, al and euery thoffentes afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, as in caſes and trial of fellony. And that the party indicted and arrained, ſhal haue aduauntage of al maner of chalenges to the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie (peremptorye chalenge only except) as in trial of felony.</p>
               <p>And alſo that euery Iuſtice of peace within the limittes of hys commiſſion ſhall haue full power and auctoritye to commit any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon being vehemently ſuſpected of any of the ſayd offences to ward, there to remayne without bayle or mainpriſe, vntil he ſhalbe deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red accordyng to this act.</p>
               <p>Prouided alwayes and be it enacted by thauctorytye aforeſayde that no maner of perſon or perſons ſhalbe moleſted, or impeched for any of thoffe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, concerning ſpeaking, or reporting as is aforeſayde
<pb facs="tcp:25971:6"/>
oneles he or they be thereof accuſed and conuicted wythin thre mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nethes, next after his or their ſayd offence ſo committed or done. And in caſe any perſon ſhalbe impryſoned for any of the ſayd offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, concerning ſpeakynge or reportyng, and not therof conuicted, within thre monethes, next after his offence ſuppoſed to be by him done and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, that then the perſon ſo impryſoned ſhalbe ſet at lyberty and no lenger deteyned in pryſon.</p>
               <p>Prouided alſo, and be it enacted by auctoritie aforeſayd, that eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye ſuche Maiour, Maiours, Bayliffes, and other heabe offycer and officers of cytyes, borowes, and townes corporate which haue or hereafter ſhall haue iuriſdiction and auctoritie, within the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral limittes of thyr office or offices, to hold and kepe ſeſſions as iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice or iuſtices of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peace ſhal, and maye by auctority hereof, aſwell arreſt &amp; commit to ward, all and euery perſon and perſons beyng vehemently ſuſpected of any of thoffences aforeſaid, as alſo to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede to the execution, hearing &amp; determining of euery y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſayd offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to ſee, and make due execution therof, according to the pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>porte, meaninge and effecte of thys preſent acte. Any thinge in the ſame act heretofore made to the contrary notwithſtandyng.</p>
               <p>Prouided alwayes, that the ſayd Iuſtice of peace, aſwel wythin liberties as without, the which ſhall for any the offences aforeſayd, commit any perſon or perſons towarde, as is aforeſayd, ſhal wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in tenne dayes next after ſuch committyng, with one other Iuſtice wherof one of them to be of the <hi>Quorum,</hi> directe theyr precepte to the Sheri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e or Sherifes of the countie where thoffence ſhalbe commit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed, or to other ordinary officer, if it be within any cyty, or town cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>porate, where the Sherife can not intromit, commaunding him or them by the ſame impanel and retourne, as they ſhal aſſigne .xxiiii. good and lawful men of hys or their bayliwike or bayliwikes to en quyre of the ſayd offence or offences the whiche any ſuch perſon or perſons ſhalbe ſo impryſoned for. And thervpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> within one moueth after the date of the ſaid precept to procede &amp; determine, as aboue is expreſſed. Euerye one of the ſame Iuſtices, vppon payne of .x.li. to be payed to the kyng and Quenes hyghneſſes, as often as they ſhalbe founden in defaulte of any the ſame.</p>
               <p>Prouyded alſo, and be it enacted, that thys act ſhalbe proclamed in al the ſhyres within thys realme, before the .xij. day of February next commyng to thintent that al perſons may haue notice therof and auoyd the peryl and daunger that myght enſue by offe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dyng agaynſt the ſame. And thys act to be only in force, vntil the ende, of the next parlyament, and no longer.</p>
               <p>Prouyded alwayes, and be it enacted by thauctorite aforeſayde, that none of the peares of thys realme ſhalbe areſted or impriſoned for any of the ſaid offences, but only by order or commaundement,
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:25971:6"/>
geuen from the kyng and quenes priuye counſayle, or of the heyres of the quene, and that the ſayd peares, and euery of them, that ſhall hereafter fortune to be indicted of any thoffences aforeſayd, ſhalbe tried by their peares, as before hathe bene accuſtomed in caſes of treaſon or fellonye.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ An act for the puniſhement of certayne perſons calling them ſelues Egiptians. ¶ The fourth Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in a parliament holden at Weſtminſter in the .xxij. yere of the reygne of our late Soueraygne lorde kyng Henry theyght (for the auoydinge &amp; banyſhyng oute o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this realme of certaine outla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſhe people, callynge them ſelues Egiptians, vſing no craft nor feate of marchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſes for to liue by, but going fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> place to place in great companies vſyng great, ſuttel, &amp; crafty meanes, to diſceaue the kynges Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, bearing them in hand, that they by palmeſtry could tel mens and womens fortune, and ſo many times by craft and ſubteltie diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the people of their money, and committed diuers great and heynous fellonyes and robberies, to the great hurt &amp; diſceyt of the people). It was amongeſt other thinges then enacted, that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the tyme of the making of the ſayde acte, no ſuche perſonnes ſhou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de be ſuffered to come within this the kynges realme, vpon payne of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feyture to the kyng al their goodes and catels, and then to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to auoyd the realme within .xv. dayes next after the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundement, vpon payne of impriſonment, &amp; ſuch perſons callyng themſelues Egiptians, as then were within thys realme, ſhoulde depart within .xvi. dayes next after proclamation of the ſayde acte vpon payne of impriſonment and forfeyture of all their goodes and cattels w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> diuers other clauſes &amp; articles co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyned in the ſayd acte, as by the ſaid act more at large it appeareth. For aſmuch as diuers of the ſayd company and ſuch other lyke perſons not fearynge the penalty of the ſayd Statute, haue enterpriſed to come ouer againe into this realme vſyng their old accuſtomed deuilyſh and noughty practiſes and deuiſes, with ſuch abhominable lyuyng as is not in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye Chriſtian realme to be permited, named, or knowen, and be not duly punyſhed for the ſame, to the peryllous and euyl exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of our ſoueraygne lord and lady the kynge and the Queenes Maieſtyes mooſte louyng ſubiectes, &amp; to the vtter and extreame vndoynge of diuers and many of them as euidently doth appeare.</p>
               <p>For reformation wherof be it ordeyned and enacted by the king and quene our ſoueraygne Lord and Lady, the Lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and the commons in preſente parliament aſſembled, and by thauctoritie of the ſame, that yf any perſon or perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25971:7"/>
laſt daye of Ianuary next commyng, do willyngly tranſport, bring and conuey into this realme of England or Waies, any ſuch perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s callynge them ſelfes or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monlye called Egiptians, that then he or they, ſo tranſporting, bringing, or conueying in, any ſuche perſons, contrary to the true meaning of this acte, ſhall forfeyte and loſe for euery tyme ſo offendyng .xl. pounds of lawful money of England.</p>
               <p>And be it further <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nacted by thauctority aforeſayd, that yf anye of the ſaid perſons called Egiptians, which ſhalbe tranſported and conueyed into this realme of England or Wales, as is aforeſaid, do continue &amp; remayne within the ſame, by the ſpace of one monethe, that then he or they ſo offending, ſhall by vertue of this acte, be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and iudged a fellon, and fellons, and ſhal therefore ſuffer pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of death, loſſe of landes &amp; goodes, as in caſes of fellony, by thor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der of the common lawe of this realme, and ſhall vpon the tryall of them, or any of them, therin, be tried in the countie, and by thinhabi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tauntes of the countie or place, where they or he ſhalbe apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded or taken, and not <hi>per medietatem linguae</hi> and ſhal loſe the benefit and priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſanctuary and clergye.</p>
               <p>And be it further enacted by thauctoritye aforeſayd, that yf the Egiptians or other perſons commonly callyng them ſelues Egip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians and euery of them now beyng within thys realme of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d or Wales, do not depart out of the ſame within .xx. daies next after proclamation of thys preſent acte ſhalbe made, that then he or they which ſhal not depart within the ſaid time, accordynge to the true meanyng of thys act, ſhal forfeyte and loſe al hys and theyr goodes and cattels, and that then it ſhalbe lawfull to al and euery the king and the Quenes ſubiectes to ſeaſe the ſame, thone moyte therof to be to the vſe of our ſoueraygne lord and lady the kyng &amp; the quene and thother moyte therof to be to the vſe of hym or the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſhal ſo ſeaſe the ſame.</p>
               <p>And be it alſo enacted by thauctority aforeſayde, that yf the Egip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians and other perſons commonly called Egiptians, and euery of them now beinge within this realme of England or Wales, do not depart out, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame, within .xl. dayes next after proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhalbe made of this act<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that then he or they, which ſhal not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, and auoyd within the ſayd time of .xl. dayes accordyng to the true meanyng of this act, ſhalbe iudged and demed accordynge to the lawes of this realme of England a fellon and fellons &amp; ſhal ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer therfore paynes of death, loſſe of landes and goodes as in other caſes of fellony and ſhalbe tryed as is aforeſayd, &amp; wythout hauing any benefite or priuilege of ſanctuary and clergie.</p>
               <p>And be it further enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayd, that yf anye perſon after the fyrſt day of Ianuarye next co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng, ſhall ſue for the obteyning of any licence, letter, or paſport, for any of the ſayde per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:25971:7"/>
called Egyptians, to abide or continue, within this realme of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande or Wales, contrary to the tenoure of this acte, that then euery ſuch perſon ſo ſuing, ſhall forfeyte and loſe for the ſame fortye ponnds of lawefull monye of Englande, and that euerye ſuche licenſe, letter and paſporte, ſhalbe by vertue of this acte, voyde, to al intentes &amp; pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, thone moytie of all whych ſummes of moneye to be forfeited, as is beforeſayde, ſhalbe to the kyng and Quene our Soueraygne Lord and Lady, and the other moyte therof to be to him or them, that wyl ſue for the ſame, in any courte of recorde, by action of decte, byl, plaint, or information, wherein any eſſoygne, wager of lawe, nor protectyon, ſhalbe admitted and allowed.</p>
               <p>Prouyded alwayes and be it enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayde, that thys preſent acte, nor any thynge therein conteyned, ſhal not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende, nor be hurtefull to any of the ſayd perſones, commonlye called Egyptians whych within the ſayde tyme of twentye dayes nexte af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſayde proclamation to be made, as is before ſaide, ſhall leaue that noughtye ydle, and vngodly lyfe, and company e, and be placed in the ſeruice of ſome honeſte and able inhabitaunte or inhabytauntes, within this realme, or that ſhal honeſtly exerciſe him ſelfe in ſome lawe full worke or occupation, but that he or they ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuing in ſeruice or other lawful worke or occupation, ſhal during ſuch time as he or they ſhall ſo continue, be diſcharged of all paynes, and forfeytures contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in this acte.</p>
               <p>Prouided alſo and be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſaide, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this acte ſhall not in any wiſe extende to anye chylde or children, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not aboue the age of .xiii. yeares, nor to any of the ſaid perſonnes, being nowe in priſon ſo that he or they ſo being in priſon, doo departe out of thys realme, within .xiiii. days next after his or their deliuery out of pryſon, nor ſhall extende to charge any maner of perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones, as acceſſary to anye offence or offences, conteined or ſpecified in this eſtatute.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ An acte to reſtrayne carriing of corne, victuals, and woodde ouer the ſea. <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> The .v. Chapyter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here as ſundrye good eſtatutes and lawes hath bene made within this realme in the tyme of the Queenes highnes moſt noble progenitours that none ſhuld tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>porte, carye or conueye oute of thys realme into anye place in the partyes beyond the ſeas any corne, butter cheſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or other victuall (excepte onelye for the vitaling of the towne of Caleys, Hames, &amp; Guyſnes, and the marches of the
<pb facs="tcp:25971:8"/>
ſame, vpon dyuerſe greate paynes and forfeytures in the ſame contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that notwithſtandyng many and ſundrye couetous and vnſacya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſones, ſekyng their onely lucres, and gaines, hath, and dayelye doeth cary and conueigh innumerable quantitie, aſwel of corne, cheſe, butter, and othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> victual, as of woode out thys realme, into the parties beyonde the ſeas. By reaſon whereof the ſayd corne, vyctuall &amp; wood are growen vnto a wonderfull dearthe, and extreame pryces, to the greate detriment of the Commonwealth of this your hyghnes realme and your faythfull ſubiectes of the ſame.</p>
               <p>For remedy whereof, it may pleaſe youre hyghnes that it maye bee enacted, and be it enacted by youre highnes by thaſſente of the lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and the commons in this preſent parlyament aſſembled, and by thauctoritie of the ſame, that no maner of perſonne or perſonnes, after the .xx. daye of Ianuary next commynge ſhall carye &amp; tranſporte out of this realme by anye Shippe, Craier, or other veſſell, whatſoeuer, into anye place in the parties beyonde the ſeas, or into the realme of Scotlande, any wheate, rye, barley, or other corne or grain, growing within this Realme, or anye malte made within the ſame, or any bere, butter, cheſe, herrynge, or wodde, excepte onely to and for the victualing and furniture of the townes of Callys, Hames, and Guyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and to the towne of Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wycke and the marches of the ſame, wyth out ſufficient and lawefull aucthoritie ſo to do, vpon the paines and pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nalties hereafter enſuinge, that is to ſaye, thowner and owners of the ſayde ſhyppes and other veſſeles, to forfeyte the ſayde ſhyppes, craiers and other veſſeles, with al their apparels, to them and euerye of them belongyng, wherein the ſayde corne, butter, cheſe, herrynge, vyctuall, or wodde, ſhalbe ſo tranſported and caryed, and the owners and owner of the ſayde corne, butter, cheſe, hearynge, and wodde to forfeyte the double valewe of the ſame, ſo caried and conueyed, and the mayſter and mareners of euery of the ſayde ſhippes craiers, and veſſells for euerye ſuche offence, to forfeyte all their goodes, and to be impryſoned, by the ſpace of one whole yeare without bayle or maynepryſe.</p>
               <p>And be it further enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayde, that yf anye perſon or perſones, after the ſayde twenty day of Ianuary do cary and conueye awaye by Boote, Crayer, or other veſſell, or otherwyſe anye wheate, rye, barleye, malte, or other corne or grayne, or any beare, but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, cheſe, herryng, or wodde to anye Shyppe or veſſell beynge on the Seas, or within any Hauen, creke, or other place of the border of thys Realme to be tranſported, caried, and conueyed into anye place in the parties beyonde the Seas, or into the realme of Scotlande, wythout ſufficient aucthoritie ſo to doo, that then euery owner of the ſayde vyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualls corne, and other thynges aboue ſayde ſoo tranſported or caryed and the owner and owners of euerye ſuche bote or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſſell, and the botemen and mareners of the ſame ſhall looſe, forfeyte, and ſuffer all
<pb n="viii" facs="tcp:25971:8"/>
ſuche forfaytures, paynes, and penaltyes as is aboue rehearſed, thone moytye of all, and euery whiche forfayture or forfaytures, to be to the Kynge and Queenes hyghnes, theyre heyres and ſucceſſours, and tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moytie to hym or them, that wyll ſue for the ſame by byll, informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, action of debte, or otherwyſe in anye of the Kynge and Queenes hyghnes courtes of recorde, in whiche action, byll, or ſuite, the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunte ſhall not wage hys lawe, nor haue any eſſoygne or protectyon to hym allowed.</p>
               <p>And be it enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayde, that yf any perſon or perſons ſhall obtayne of the kynge and Queenes maieſties, their hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res or ſucceſſoures, or of any of them, any licence to cary and tranſporte any corne, victuall, or wodde, into any parties beyonde the ſeas, that if he or they, to whome any ſuch licence, ſhalbe graunted, or any other, to whome ſuch perſon or perſones, hauynge ſuch licence, ſhall gyue, grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell his or their ſaid licence vnto, ſhall cary, and conueye or cauſe to be caried and conueyed any more corne, victuall, or woodde then ſhalbe conteined in hys or their ſayd licence ſhall forfeyte the treble value<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of the ſayde corne, victuall, or woode ſo caried and tranſported, wythoute ſufficient authoritie, and ſhall ſuffer impriſonment for one whole yeare in the common gaole, where he ſhalbe apprehended, there to remayne without bayle or maynepryſe.</p>
               <p>And be it further enacted by thaucthorite aforeſayde, that no ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of perſon or perſones, after the ſayde .xx. day of Ianuary, that ſhall obteyne, or haue any ſuch licence for tranſportynge and carienge anye corne victuall or wodde, into any parties beyonde the ſeas, ſhal ſhippe lade, and fraughte the ſame, or anye parte thereof, at ſondrye places within this realme, but at one place certayne, vpon payne of forfeyture of the ſayde corne, victuall &amp; wodde, and all his goods &amp; cattels thone moytie there of to the Kynge and Quenes maieſties, their heires and ſucceſſours, and thother moytie to him or them that wyll ſue for the ſame by action of debte, byll playnt information or otherwyſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in no wager of lawe, eſſoygne or protection ſhalbe to hym or them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed.</p>
               <p>And for the better executyon of this acte, be it further enacted by the aucthorytie aforeſayde, that all and ſynguler Iuſtyces of peace, as well within the liberties as withoute, within their ſeuerall aucthorityes and commyſſions at any tyme, with in three yeares nexte after ſuche offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces committed, ſhall haue full power and aucthorytie to enquire as well by the othes of twelue lawfull men, as alſo to heare and examyne the mayſter, maiſtres, and mareners of the ſayd ſhyppes, crayers, &amp; other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſels, and all, and euerye other perſone and perſones, of all, and ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler thoffenders agaynſt this preſente Acte, and to heare and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the ſame offences, as they maye, and ought to here and determine any other treſpaſſes, or offences.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25971:9"/>
Prouyded alwayes, and be it enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayde, that at all time and tymes hereafter, when the common price of corne within this realme is, that wheate ſhall not exceade the pryce of .vi. s. viii. d. the quarter, and rye .iiii. s, the quarter, and bareleye. iii, ſhillings the quarter, it ſhalbe lawefull to euery perſon and perſoues to cary and tranſporte ouer the ſea, to any place beyonde the ſeas at their pleaſure of the ſayde kyndes of corne, ſo that it be not to the Kyng and Quenes enemyes.</p>
               <p>Prouided alwayes, and be it enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayde, that thys Acte, ne any thinge therein contained, ſhall extende to anye perſon or perſones for the neceſſary victeling of any ſhyppe, ſhyppes, or other veſſeles, but that they, and euery of them, maye victayle the ſaid ſhyppes and veſſels, as they myght haue done before the makynge of this preſent acte. This acte or any thynge therein conteined to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary notwithſtanding.</p>
               <p>Prouyded alwayes, and be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayde, that this acte, or any thinge therein conteined, ſhall not be preiudicyall or hurtefull vnto the Lorde greate admirall of Englande, for the time beinge, or to the Kynge and Queenes maieſties iuriſdiction of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miraltie, but that the ſayde Lord Admiral, or his deputie, or deputies, maye, and ſhall exercyſe, vſe, and execute all kynde of iuriſdiction, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longyng to the ſea accordyng to his or their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſions, as they might lawefullye haue done heretofore. This acte, or any thinge therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned to the contrary notwithſtandyng.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ An Acte for the reuiuing of three Eſtatutes made for the punyſhment of hereſies. The .vi. Chapyter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the eſchuing and auoydyng of errours &amp; hereſyes, whych of late haue ryſen, growen, and muche increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed within this realme, for that the Ordinaryes haue wanted aucthoritie to procede agaynſte thoſe, that wer infected therewith. Be it therefore ordeyned and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted by the aucthoritie of thys preſente parliamente, that the Statute made in the fyfte yere of the reigne oi kyng Richard the ſeconde, concernynge the arreſting and apprehenſion of erronyous and hereticall preachers, and one other Statute, made in the ſeconde yeare of the reigne of kyng Henry the fourth, concernynge repreſſing of hereſies, and punyſhmente of heretikes, and alſo one other Eſtatute made in the Seconde yere of the raynge of Kynge Henrye the fyfte, concernynge the ſuppreſſyon of hereſye and lollardye, and euerye Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, Braunche, and ſentence conteigned in the ſame three ſeuerall
<pb n="ix" facs="tcp:25971:9"/>
actes, and euery of them, ſhall from the twenty daye of Ianuary nexte comming, be reuiued, and be in full force, ſtrengthe, and effecte, to all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intentes, conſtructions &amp; purpoſes, for euer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The tenor of the acte, made in the fiueth yere of kyng Richard, is as foloweth. Chapiter .v.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Tem foraſmuch as it is openlye knowen, that there be diuers euil perſones within the realme goyng from cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie to countie, and from towne to towne, in certayne ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites, vnder dyſſimulation of greate holynes, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the licence of the Ordinaryes of the places, or other ſufficient ancthoritie: prechyng dayly, not onely in chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches and churchyards, but alſo in markets, Faires, &amp; otheropen places where a great congregacion of people is, diuers ſermones conteining hereſies, and notorius erroures, to the greate embleamiſhynge of the chryſten fayth, and deſtruction of the Lawes, and of the eſtate of holye Churche, to the greate pericle of the ſoules of the people, and of al the realme of Englande, as more playnely is founde, and ſufficientlye pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyd, before the reuerent father in God the Archebiſhop of Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, and the Biſhoppes, and other prelates, mayſters of diuinitie, and doctoures, of Canon and of ciuile, and a greate parte of the clergye of the ſayde realme, ſpecially aſſembled for this cauſe, whych perſones do alſo preach diuers matters of ſlaunder, to engender diſcorde and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention betwixt diuers eſtates, of the ſaid realme, aſwelſpiritual as te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral in exciting of the people to the greate peril of al the realme, which preachers cited or ſommoned before the ordinaries of the places, there to aunſwere of that where of they be impeched, wil not obeye to there ſummons and commaund ements, nor care not for their monicions nor Senſures of the holy churche, but expreſſely diſpiſe them. And moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, by their ſubtyl and ingenious wordes, do draw the people to here their Sermons, and do maintayne them in their errours by ſtronge hand, and by greate routes. It is ordeined and aſſented in this preſent Parliament that the kynges commiſſions be made and directed to the Sheryffes and other miniſters of our ſouer aygne Lorde the kinge or other ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t perſones learned, and accordyng to the certificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prelates thereof to be made in the Chauncery, from tyme to tyme to ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reſt al ſuch preachers, and alſo their fautours, mainteiners, and abbet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, and to holde them in arreſt and ſtrong priſon, tyll they wyll iuſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fye them, accordyng to the lawe and reaſon of holy Church. And the kynge wyll and commaundeth, that the Chauncelloure make ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſyons at all tymes, that he by the prelates, or any of them ſhall be cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyfyed, and thereof required, as is aforeſayde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:25971:10"/>
               <head>¶ The tenor of the ſeconde acte, made in the ſecond yeare of kynge Henry the .iiii. is as foloweth. Cha. xv.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Tem where as it is ſhewed to oure Soueraygne Lorde the kynge, on the behalfe of the prelates and Clergye of hys realme of Englande in this preſente Parlyamente, that although the catholyke fayth buylded vpon Chryſte and by his Apoſtles, and the holy churche ſuffycyentelye determined, declared, and approued, hathe bene hether to by good and holy, and moſte noble progenitoures of oure ſoueraigne Lorde the kynge in the ſaied Realme, emongeſte all the realmes of the worlde, mooſte deuoutlye obſerued, and the Churche of Englande, by his ſayd moſte noble progenitours and aunceſtoures, to the honoure of God, and the whole Realme aforeſayde, laudablye endowed, and in her ryghtes and lyberties ſuſteined, without that that the ſame faith, or the ſayde Churche was hurte or greuouſlye oppreſſed, or ells perturbed by anye peruerſe doctrine, or wycked hereticall or erronious opinions, yet neuertheleſſe dyuers falſe and peruerſe people, of a certayne new ſecte of the fayth of, the Sacramentes of the Churche, and the aucthorytye of the ſame, damuably thinkynge and agaynſt the lawe of GOD, and of the churche, vſurpyng the offyce of preachynge do peruerſlye and mali<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciouſlye, in dyuerſe places within the ſayde realme, vnder the colour of diſſimuled holynes, preach and teach theſe dayes openlye and priuelye, diuers newe doctryues, and mycked heretical and erronious opinions contrarye to the ſame faythe, and bleſſed determinacions of the holye Churche. And of ſuche ſecte and wycked doctryne and opinions, they make vnlawefull conuenticles, and confederacies, they holde and exer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyſe ſcholes, they make and wrytte bokes, they do wickedly inſtructe &amp; infourme people, and aſmuche as they maye excite and ſtirre them to ſedition and inſurrection, and maketh great ſtryfe and diuiſion emonge the people, and other enormities horrible to be heard, daylye doo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrate and commit, in ſubuercion of the ſayde catholyke faith, and do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctryne of the holy churche, in diminucion of Gods honoure, and alſo in deſtruccion of the eſtate, ryghtes, and liberties of the ſayde churche of Englande, by which ſecte and wycked and falſe preachynges, doctry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and opmions of the ſayde falſe and peruerſe people, not onely moſt greateſt peryll of the ſoules, but alſo manye more other hurtes, ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and peryles (whych God prohibite) myghte come to thys realme onleſſe it be the more ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifullye and ſpedely holpen by the kynges ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie in this behalfe, namely where as the dioceſans of the ſayd realme cannot by their iuriſdiction ſpirituall without ayde of the ſayde royall Maieſtie, ſufficientlye correcte the ſayde falſe and peruerſe people, nor refrayne their malice, becauſe the ſayd falſe and peruerſe people do go from Dyoces to Dyoces, and wyll not appeare before the ſayde Dioce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſans, but the ſame Dioceſans, and their iuriſdiction ſpirituall, and the
<pb n="x" facs="tcp:25971:10"/>
kayes of the churche, with the cenſures of the ſame, doo vtterlye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e and diſpiſe, and ſoo their wicked preachynges and doctrines, doeth from daye to daye continue and exerciſe, to the hatrede of right and reaſon, and vtter deſtruction ordre and good rule. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon whyche nowelties and exceſſes aboue reherſed. The Prelates and clergye aforeſayd, and alſo the commons of the ſayd realme, being in the ſame parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, praying our ſoueraigne Lord the king, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> his roial highnes woulde voucheſafe in the ſayde parliamente to prouyde a conueniente remedie, the ſame our ſoueraygne Lord the kyng, gratiouſlye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng the premiſſes, and alſo the laudable ſteppes of his ſayde moſte no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble progenitiours and aunceſtours, for the conſeruation of the ſaid ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyke faythe, and ſuſtentation of Goddes honour, and alſo the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde of the eſtate, ryghtes, and liberties of the ſayde Churche of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande, to the laude of God, and mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e of our ſayde ſoueraygne lorde the kynge, and proſperitie &amp; honour of all his ſayde realme, and for the eſchewinge of ſuche diſſentions, diuiſions, hurtes, ſlaunders, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryles, in tyme to come, and that this wicked ſecte, preachynges, doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trynes and opinions, ſhoulde from hence for the ceaſe, and be vtterlye deſtroyed, by thaſſente of the ſtates, &amp; other diſcrete men of the realme beyng in the ſayde parliament, hath graunted, ſtabliſhed, and ordeined fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> henceforth, fermely to be obſerued, that none within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid realme or any other dominions, ſubiectes to his royall maieſtie, preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e to prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che openly or priuelye without the licence of the Dioceſan of the ſame place, fyrſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e required and obteined, curates in their owne churches, &amp; perſones hetherto priuileged, and other of the canon lawe graunted, onelye excepte. Nor that none from henceforthe anye thynge preache, holde teache, or inſtruct, openly or priuelye, or make or wrytte any boke contrarye to the catholyke fayth or determination of the holy church<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nor of ſuche ſecte and wicked doctrines and opinions, ſhall make anye conuenticles, or in any wyſe holde or exercyſe Scholes. And alſo that none from hence forth in any wyſe fauoure ſuche preacher, or maker of any ſuch, and lyke conuenticles, or holdynge or exercyſynge ſcholes, or makynge or writing ſuche bokes, or ſo teachynge infourmynge, or exciting the people nor any of them maintaine, or in anye wiſe ſuſteyne And that al, and ſinguler hauynge ſuche bookes or anye wrytynges of ſuch wycked doctrine and opinions, ſhall really with effecte delyuer, or cauſe to be deliuered al ſuche bokes and writinges to the Dyoceſan of the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> lace, within .xl. dayes from the tyme of the proclamation of thys ordinaunce and ſtatute. And yfany perſon or perſones, of whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer kynde, eſtate, or condition that he or they be from henceforth do or attempte agaynſt the roial ordinaunce &amp; ſtatute aforeſaid in the premiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes or in any of them or ſuche bokes in the fourme aforeſaid do not deli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer, then the dioceſan of the ſame place in his dioces, ſuche perſonne or perſones in this behalfe defamed, or euidently ſuſpected &amp; euerye of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25971:11"/>
may by the aucthoritie of the ſayde ordinary and Statute, cauſe to be arreſted, and vnder ſaufe cuſtody in his priſones to be deteined, tyll he or they of the articles layed to him or them in this behalfe, doo canony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>callye purge him or themſelfe, or ells ſuch wycked ſecte, preachynges, doctrynes, and hereticall and erromous opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, do abiure, according as the lawes of the churche, doth require, ſo that the ſayde dyoceſan by him ſelfe, or his commiſſaryes, do openly and iudicially procede againſt ſuch perſones ſo arreſted, and remaynynge vnder his ſauſe cuſtodye to all effecte of the lawe, and determine that ſame buſines, accordynge to the Canonicall decrees, within three monethes after the ſayde arreſte any lawefull impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ceaſſynge. And yf any perſon in any caſe aboue expreſſed, be before the dioceſan of that place, or his commiſſaryes ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicallye conuicte, then the ſame dioceſan may do to be kept in his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the ſayde perſon ſo conuicte, for the maner of his default, and after the qualitie of the offence, accordyng and as longe as to his dyſcretyon ſhall ſeme expediente, and moreouer to put the ſame perſon to the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar court, excepte in caſes where he accordyng to the canonicall decree ought to be left, to paye to our ſoueraygne lorde the kyng, his pecunier fine, accordyng as the ſame fyne ſhall ſeme competente to the dyoceſan, for the maner and qualitie of the offence, in whyche caſe the ſame dyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſan, ſhalbe bounde to certifye the kynge of the ſame fine in hys eſche ker, by his Lettre Patentes, ſealed with his ſeale, to the effecte that ſuche fyne by the kynges aucthoritie, maye be required and leuyed to his vſe of the goodes of the ſame perſon ſo conuycte. And yf any perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> within the ſayd realme and dominions, vpon the ſayde wycked prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynges, doctrynes, opinions, ſchooles, and hereticall and erronious informations, or any of them be before the dioceſan of the ſame place, or his commiſſaryes ſentenciallye conuicte &amp; the ſame wicked ſect, prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chynges, doctrynes, and opinions, ſcholes, and informations, do refuſe duelye to abiure, or by the dyoceſan of the ſame place or his commyſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes after the abiuration made by the ſame perſon pronounced, fal into relapſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o that accordynge to the holy canons, he oughte to be left to the ſeculer courte, wherevpon credence ſhalbe geuen to the Dyoceſan of the ſame place, or to his commiſſaryes, in thys behalfe, then the ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryffe of the countie of the ſame place, and Maior and ſheryffes or ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rife, or Mayor and Baylyffes of the Citie, Towne, and borowe of the ſame countie nexte to the ſame dioceſan, or the ſayde Commiſſaryes, ſhalbe perſonallye preſente in preferrynge of ſuch ſentences, when they by the ſame dioceſan, or his commiſſaryes ſhalbe required, and they the ſame perſonnes and euerye of them, after ſuche ſentence promulgate, ſhall receaue, and them before the people in an hyghe place dooe to be brente: that ſuche punyſhmente maye ſtrike in feare to the myndes of other, whereby no ſuch wycked doctrine and hereticall, and erronious opinions, nor their abbettoures and fautoures in the ſaid realme &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions
<pb n="xv" facs="tcp:25971:11"/>
agaynſt the catholike faith, chriſten lawe &amp; determination of the holy church (which god prohibite) be ſuſteined, or in any wiſe ſuffered, in which al and ſinguler the premiſſes, concerning the ſaid ordinaunce and ſtatute, the ſheriffes, maiors, and baliffes of the ſaid counties, cities, boroughes, and townes, ſhalbe tendyng, aydynge, and ſupportyng, to the ſayd dioceſans and their commiſſaries.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The tenor of the third act, made in the ſecond yere of kynge Henry the fift, is as foloweth. Cap. vii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Tem foraſmuch as great rumors, congregations, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrections here in the realme of England by diuers of the kinges liege people, aſwel by them which wer of the ſect of hereſies co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly called lollardry, as by other of their confederatie, excitation, &amp; abbetment, now of late were made to the intent to adnul, diſtroy, and ſubuerte the chriſten faythe, and the law of god and holy Churche within this ſame realme of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, &amp; alſo to deſtroye the ſame our ſoueraygne lord the kyng, &amp; all other maner of eſtates of the ſame realme of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, aſwel ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al as temporal, and alſo al maner of policye and finally the lawes of the land. The ſame our ſoueraygne lorde the kyng, to the honor of god, &amp; in conſeruation &amp; fortification of the chriſten faithe, &amp; alſo in ſaluation of hys royal eſtate, &amp; of the eſtate of al his realme, willing agaynſt the malice of ſuch heretikes &amp; lollardes to prouide a more open remedy &amp; puniſhement then hathe bene had &amp; vſed in the caſe hertofore, ſo that for feare of the ſame lawes and puniſhement ſuch hereſies and lollardries may y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> rather ceaſe in tyme to come, by the aduiſe &amp; aſſent aforeſayd, at the praier of the ſayde commons hath ordeyned &amp; eſtabliſhed: that fyrſt the chaunceler, treaſurer Iuſtices of the one bench and of the other, Iuſtices of peace ſhirefes, maiors, and baylifes of cities and townes, and al other officers, hauing go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernance of people, which now be, or hereafter for the tyme ſhalbe, ſhal make an oth in taking of theyr charges and occupatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, to put their hole power &amp; diligence, to put out &amp; do to be put out, ceaſe, &amp; deſtroy al maner of hereſies &amp; errours, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly called lollardries, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in the places wher they exerciſe their offices &amp; occupations from tyme to tyme w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al their power, and that they aſſiſte the ordinaryes and their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſaries &amp; them fauor &amp; maintaine as often as they or any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhalbe required by the ſame ordinaries or their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſaries, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> when the ſaid officers &amp; miniſters trauayle or ride to arreſt any lollard, or to make aſſiſtence at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inſtance &amp; requeſt of the ordinaries or their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſaries by vertue of this ſtatute y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the ſame ordinaries &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſaries ſhal pay for their coſtes reaſonable. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the kyngs ſeruices to the which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame offycers be fyrſt ſworne, be
<pb facs="tcp:25971:12"/>
preferred before al other ſtatutes for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> libertie of holy church, &amp; the miniſters of the ſame, &amp; in eſpicial for the correction &amp; puniſhmente of the heretikes and lollardes before this time made &amp; not repelled being in their force. And alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> al perſons co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uict of hereſie, of what eſtate, condition or degre y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be, by the ſayd ordinaries or other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſaries left to the ſeculer power, according to the lawes of holy church, ſhal loſe and forfeyt al theyr lands and tenementes, whiche they haue in fee ſimple in the maner as foloweth, that is to ſay, that the king haue al the lands &amp; tenementes, which the ſayd conuictes haue in fee ſimple &amp; holden of him immediatly as forfeyt, &amp; that the other lords, of whom the lands &amp; tenementes of ſuch conuictes be holden immediatly, after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the kyng is ſo ſeaced &amp; anſwered of the yere the day, and the waſt, haue liuery our of the kynges handes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> landes &amp; teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes aforeſaid of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as it hath bene vſed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caſe of attainder of felonie, except y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> landes &amp; teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, which be holden of t he ordinaries or their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſaries, before whome any ſuch perſons impeched of hereſie be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uict, which landes &amp; teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>rly ſhal remayne to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyng as forfayte. And moreouer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goods &amp; cattels of theſe perſons ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uicted, be forfait to our ſoue raygne lord the kyng, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no perſon conuict of hereſy, &amp; left to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer power after the lawes of holy church, ſhal for feyt his la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he be dead. And if any ſuch perſon ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uict be enfeffed be it by fyne by dede, or w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out dede in la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des or tenementes, rentes or ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in fee or otherwyſe, or hath any other poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or catels by gift or grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of any perſon or perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to anothers vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe of ſuch conuictes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the ſame lands nor tenementes, re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes nor ſeruices, nor ſuch other poſſeſſions, nor catels ſhalbe forfeit to our ſoueraign lord the king in no wiſe. And moreouer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the iuſtices of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kings bench, &amp; iuſtices of pece, &amp; iuſtices of aſſiſe, haue ful power to enquire of al the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which hold anierrors or hereſies, as lollards, &amp; which be their main teine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, receyuers, fauorers &amp; ſuſteyners co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men writers of ſuch bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes, aſwel of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſermons, as of their ſcoles, conue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ticles, congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and confede racies. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thys clauſe be put in commiſſions of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peace. And if any perſons be indicted of any points afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd iuſtices ſhal haue power to award againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a <hi>capias</hi> and the ſhiref ſhalbe bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to arreſt the perſon or perſons ſo endicted as ſone as he mai the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ynd by him or by his officers. And foraſmuch as the cogniſance of hereſy, errors &amp; lollardries, belongeth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudges of holy church, &amp; not to the ſeculer Iudges, ſuche perſons indicted ſhalbe delyuered to the ordinaries of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> places or to theyr commyſſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryes, by indentures betwyxt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be made, wythin .x. dayes after theyr arreſt, or ſoner yf it may be, therof to be acquit or conuict by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawes of holy church, in caſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe perſons be not indicted o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thyng, wherof y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cognyſaunce belongeth to the ſeculer iudges
<pb n="xii" facs="tcp:25971:12"/>
and officers, in whiche caſe, after that, that they be acquyte or dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered before the ſeculer Iudges of ſuch thinges to the ſeculer Iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges belongyng, they ſhalbe ſent in ſafegarde to the ſayde ordinary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, or to their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſaries, and to them deliuered by indentures as before, to be acquite or conuict of ſuch lollardries, errours, or here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, as is aforeſayd, after the lawes of holy churche, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the terme aforeſayde.</p>
               <p>Prouided alwayes that the ſayde endictementes be not taken in euidence but for information before the ſpirituall Iudges agaynſt ſuche perſons ſo endicted, but that the ordinaries commence theyr proceſſe agaynſt ſuch perſons endicted in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame maner as though no endictment were, hauyng no regarde to ſuch endictmentes.</p>
               <p>And yf anye be endicted of hereſye, errour, or lollardrye, and taken by the Shyreffe or other officer, he ſhalbe let to maynpryce wythin the ſayde tenne dayes by good ſuerty, for whom the ſayd ſhyreffes or other officers wyl aunſwere, ſo that the ſayde perſon or perſons, which were ſo endicted, be ready to be deliuered to the ſayde ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries or to their commiſſaries, before the ende of the ſayde tenne dayes, yf he may by any meanes for ſyckenes. And euery ordinarye ſhal haue ſufficient commiſſaries, or commiſſary dwellyng in euery countie in a place notable, ſo that if any ſuch perſon ſo endicted be ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken, that the ſayde commiſſaryes or commiſſarie, may be warned in the notable place where he dwelleth by the ſhyreffe, or ſome of hys officers, to come to the kynges iayle in the ſame countie, there to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyue the ſame perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo endicted by indentures as before. And that in the inqueſt in thys caſe to be taken, the ſhyreffes and other offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, to whome it beloogeth ſhal do to be empanelled good and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cient perſons, not ſuſpected nor procured, that is to ſay, that euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ſhalbe ſo empanelled in ſuche inqueſt, haue wythin the realme of England .C. s. of landes, tenementes, or of rent by yere, vpon payne to loſe to the kynges vſe .x. li. and thei which ſhalbe em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panelled in ſuch inqueſtes in Wales, euery of them ſhal haue to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lue of .xl. s. by yeare. And yf anye ſuche perſon be arreſt, be it by the ordinary, or by the kynges officers or miniſters, &amp; eſcape or breake the priſon, before y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he be acquit before the ordinary the goodes and cattels whiche he hadde the daye of ſuche arreſte, ſhalbe forfeyte to the kynge, and hys landes and tenementes, whych he had the ſame daye ſeaſed alſo into the kynges handes, the kyng ſhal haue the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fytes therof from the ſayd day, vntyl he be yelded to the pryſon fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which he eſcaped. And that the forſayd Iuſtices haue ful power to enquire of al ſuch eſcapes, breakyng of pryſon, and alſo of lands and tenementes, goodes and cattels of ſuch perſons ſo endicted.</p>
               <p>Prouided alſo that yf any ſuch perſon endicted do not retorne to the ſayd priſon and dieth not conuict it ſhalbe lawfull to his heyres
<pb facs="tcp:25971:13"/>
to enter into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> landes and tenementes of their aunceſtre, without any other purſuyt makynge to the kyng for thys cauſe, and then al they which haue libe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tyes and fraunchiſes royall in England, as in the countie of Cheſter, the countie and liberty of Durham, &amp; other lyke, and alſo al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lordes, which haue iuriſdiction and fraunchiſns royal in Wales, where the kynges writtes do not run, haue power to execute and put in due executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe articles in al pointes by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or by theyr officers, in like maner as the Iuſtices and other the kin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges offycers before declared ſhoulde doe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ An act that perſons dwellyng in the countrey, ſhal not ſel diuers wares in cities or townes corporate by retayle. ¶ The .vii. Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>VHere before this tyme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> auncient cities, boroughes townes corporat, and market townes within thys realme of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, haue bene very populous, &amp; chief<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly inhabited with marchantes, artificers, &amp; handye craftes me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, during which time y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſayd cities, borowes, townes corporat, &amp; market townes were ciuilly brought vp, and inſtructed, and alſo the ſayd cities, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes and townes corporate, kept in good order and obeyſaunce, and the inhabiters of the ſame wel ſet on worke, and kept from ydle nes. By reaſon wherof the ſayde cytyes, borowes and townes cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate, did then proſper in riches and great wealth, &amp; were as then not only able to ſerue and furnyſh the kyng and quenes maieſties, and other their noble progenitours kynges of thys realme, aſwell with great numbers of good able perſons, and wel furnyſhed mete for the wares, as alſo then charged, and yet chargeable, with great fee farmes, quindemes, taxes, and diuers other paymentes to the kyng and Quenes maieſties, which at this preſent they be not able to paye &amp; beare, but to their vtter vndoing, beyng fewe in number to paye and bear the ſame, but alſo the ſame cities, boroughes, and townes corporat, are lyk to come very ſhortly to vtter dyſtruction ruyne, and decay, by reaſon whereof the occupyers, linnen drapers wollen drapers haberdaſhars, and grocers, dwellinge in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries out of the ſaid cities, boroughes, townes corporate, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket townes, do not onely occupye the art and miſtery of the ſaid ſci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ences, in the places wher they dwell and inhabite, but alſo come vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the ſaid cities, boroughes, townes corporat and market townes and ther ſell their wares, and take away the releif of the inhabitau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of the ſayd cities, borowes, townes corporate, and market tow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, to the great decaye, and vtter vndoyng of the inhabitantes of
<pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:25971:13"/>
the ſame, yf ſpedy reformation therin be not had in time conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. For remedy whereof, &amp; for the better amendment of the ſayde citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, boroughes, townes corporate, &amp; market townes, and to thend the ſame cities, boroughes, and townes corporat, may be the better able to pay the ſayd fee farmes, and alſo to beare the other ordinary charges within the ſame cities, boroughes, and townes corporate, and to furnyſhe the kyng and queenes maieſtyes, with numbres of able perſons, like as they heretofore haue done in times paſt, in ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of warre.</p>
               <p>Be it therfore enacted by our ſoueraygne Lord and Ladye, the kyng and Quene, the lordes ſpirituall and temporal, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in this preſent parlyament aſſembled, and by thauctoryty of ſame, that any perſon or perſons which do nowe inhabite &amp; dwell, or hereafter ſhal inhabite or dwel in the country any wher or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in thys realme of Englande, out of any of the ſayd cities, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughes, townes corporate, or market townes, from &amp; after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feaſt of S. Michael tharchangel next commyng, ſhall not ſell or cauſe to be ſold by retayle, any wollen cloth, linnen cloth, haberdaſhe wares grocery wares, marcery wares, at or within any of the ſayd cities, boroughes, townes corporat, or market townes, or w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſuburbes or liberties of the ſayde cities, boroughes, townes corporat, &amp; mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket townes within the ſayd realme of England (except it be in open fayres) vpon payne to forfeyt &amp; loſe for euery time ſo offending the ſumme of .vi. s. viii. d. &amp; the whole wares ſo ſolde, profered and offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be ſold, contrary to the forme, entente and effect of thys pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent act, as aboue is ſayd, the one moyte of al whiche forfeytures to be to the vſe of our ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſoue raygne lorde and ladye the kynge and quenes maieſties, and the other halfe to hym or them that ſhal ſeaſe and ſue for the ſame in any of the kynge and queenes courtes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, by byl, playnt, action of debt, information or otherwyſe, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in no eſſoygne, proteccion or wager of law ſhalbe allowed.</p>
               <p>Prouided alway, that this acte ſhall not in any wyſe extende, nor be hurtful to any perſon or perſons, that bryng any of the ſayd wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len cloth, li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en cloth, haberdaſh grocerye, mercery, ware or wares, to any of the ſayd cities, boroughes, townes corporate, or markette townes to be ſolde, or cauſe to be ſolde, by whole ſale, in groſſe and not by retayle, but they and euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may lawfully ſel the ſame, in as large and ample maner, forme, and condition by whole ſale in groſſe, &amp; not by retayle, as they and euery of them might haue done at any tyme or tymes before the makyng of thys acte. Anye thinge herein to the contrary not withſtandinge.</p>
               <p>Prouided alway that thys preſent acte ſhall not extende to anye perſon or perſons, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> now dwel or inhabite in the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try, or herafter
<pb facs="tcp:25971:14"/>
ſhal dwel or inhabite out of any of the ſayd cities, borowes, townes corporate, or market townes, but that they, and euerye of them at any tyme hereafter, when they or any of them ſhalbe fre of any the guyldes, &amp; libertyes, of any the ſayd cities, borowes, townes corpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rate, or market towns, and dwel or inhabite within any of the ſame cities, borowes, townes corporate, or markette townes, that they and euery of them ſo beyng free, ſhal and may ſel or cauſe to be ſolde any of the wares aforſayd, by retayle, in as ample and large maner as they and euery of them might haue done, beyng free of the ſayde cities, borowes, and townes a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oreſayd, before the makyng of thys acte. Any clauſe or article in thys act to the contrarye notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge.</p>
               <p>Prouyded alwayes, and be it enacted by thauetoritye aforeſaid that it ſhalbe laweful to al perſons, to ſell or cauſe to be ſolde by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle or otherwyſe, al maner of cloth, linnen or wollen of their owne making in euery city, borough, towne corporat, and market towne within the realme, as frelye and francklye as they might haue done before the makyng of thys acte. Any thynge in the ſame conteyned to the contrary hereof notwithſtandyng.</p>
               <p>Prouided alway that thys act or any thyng therein conteyned ſhal not be preiudicial or hurtfull to the liberties, and priuileges of the vniuerſities of Cambridge and Oxford, or eyther of them. Any thyng in thys act heretofore mencioned to the contrary notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ An acte repealyng all Statutes, articles, and prouiſions made agayn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t the Sea Apoſtolike of Rome, ſynce the .xx. yeare of kyng Henry the eyght, and alſo for the eſtabliſhment of al ſpiritual and eccleſiſtical poſſeſſions and heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamentes conueyed to the laytie. ¶ The eyght Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>VHere as ſynce the .xx. yere of kynge Henry theight of famous memory, father vnto youre maieſtie, our moſt naturall ſoueraygne, and gratious Lady and Queene, muche falſe and erronious doctryne, hath bene taught, preached, &amp; written partly by dyuers the natural borne ſubiectes of this realme &amp; parte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beyng brought in hether from ſondry other forreyne countryes hath bene ſowen &amp; ſpred abroad within the ſame. By reaſon wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of aſwel the ſpiritualtie as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temporaltie of your highnes realmes and dominions haue ſwerued from the obedience of the ſea Apoſto lyke, and declined from the vnitie of Chriſtes churche, and ſo haue
<pb n="xiiii" facs="tcp:25971:14"/>
continued vntyl ſuch time as your maieſtye beyng fyrſte reyſed vp by god, and ſet in the ſeate Royall ouer vs, and then by hys deuine &amp; gratious prouidence knit in mariage with the moſte noble &amp; ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous prynce, the kyng oure ſoueraygne lorde youre huſbande, the Popes holynes and the Sea apoſtolyke ſent hyther vnto your ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ieſtyes (as vnto perſons vndefiled, &amp; by gods goodnes preſerued from the common infection aforeſayd) and to the whole realme, the moſte reuerende father in God, the lorde Cardinall Poole Legate <hi>de latere,</hi> to cal vs home agayne into the ryght way, from whence we haue al thys long while, wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred and ſtrayed abrode. And we after ſundrye longe, and greuous plagues and calamities, ſeynge by the goodnes of god our owne errours, haue knowledged the ſame vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſayd mooſte reuerend father, and by hym haue bene, and are the rather at the contemplacion of your maieſtyes, receyued &amp; em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced into the vnitie and boſome of Chriſtes church, and vpon our humble ſubmiſſion &amp; promiſe made for a declaration of oure repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce to repeale and abrogate ſuch actes and ſtatutes as had bene made in parliament ſynce the ſayd .xx. yere of the ſayd kyng Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry theyght, agaynſt the ſupremacy of the Sea apoſtolyke, as in our ſubmiſſion exhibited to the ſayd moſte reuerende father in God, by your maieſtyes appeareth. The tenor wherof enſueth.</p>
               <p>We the lordes ſpiritual and temporall, and the commons aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in thys preſent parlyament, repreſentyng the whole body of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> realme of Englande, and the dominions of the ſame, in the name of our ſelues perticulerly and alſo of the ſayd body vniuerſally in this our ſupplication directed to your maieſtyes with moſt humble ſuit that it may by your graces interceſſion &amp; meane be exhibited to the moſt reuerende father in God. the lorde cardynall Poole Legate, ſent ſpeciallye hyther from our mooſte holye father Pope Iuly the thyrd, and the Sea apoſtolyke of Rome, do declare our ſelues very ſory and repentaunte, of the ſciſme and diſobedience, committed in thys realme &amp; dominions aforeſayd, againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd Sea apoſtolike eyther by making, agreing, or exec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yng any lawes, ordinaunces, or commaundementes agaynſt the ſupremacy of the ſayd ſea, or other wyſe doyng or ſpeakyng, that might impugne the ſame: offerynge ourſelues, &amp; promyſing by thys our ſupplication, that for a token &amp; knowledge of our ſayd repentaunce, we be &amp; ſhalbe alwayes ready vnder and with thauctorities of your maieſties, to the vttermoſt of our powers, to do that ſhall lye in vs, for the abrogation and repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng of the ſayde lawes and ordinances in this preſent parlyament aſwel for our ſelues as for the whole bodye, whome we repreſente, whervpon we moſt humblye deſyre your maieſtyes as perſonages vndefiled in thoffence of hys body towardes the ſayd Sea, whych neuertheles god by hys prouidence, hath made ſubiect to you, ſo to
<pb facs="tcp:25971:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſet forth this our moſt humble ſuyte, that we may obtayne from the Sea apoſtolyke, by the ſayde moſt reuerend father, aſwell perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerly, as generally, abſolution, releaſe, and diſcharge, from al daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ſuch cenſures, and ſentences, as by the lawes of the churche we be fallen into. And that we may as children repentaunt, be recei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued into the boſome and vnitie of Chriſtes churche, ſo as this noble realme with al the membres therof, may in this vnitie, and perfect obedience to the Sea apoſtolyke, and Popes, for the tyme beynge, ſerue god and your maieſties, to the furtherance and aduaunceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his honor and glory. We are at the interceſſion of your maieſties by thauctoritye of our holy father Pope Iuly the thyrd, and of the Sea apoſtolike, aſſoiled, diſcharged and deliuered from excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, interdictions and other cenſures eccleſiaſtical, which hath hanged ouer our heades for our ſayde defaultes ſynce the tyme of the ſayde ſciſme mencioned in our ſupplication. The whyche tyme the ſayde lorde Legate and we do al declare, recogniſe, and meane by thys act to be onely ſynce the .xx. year of the raigne of your moſt noble father kyng Henry the eyght. It maye now lyke your maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties, that for the accompliſhment of our promyſe made in the ſayde ſupplication, that is, to repeale al lawes &amp; ſtatutes mode contrarye to the ſayde ſupremacy and Sea apoſtolyke, durynge the ſayd ſciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, the whych is to be vnderſtande, ſynce the .xx. yere of the raygne of the ſayd late kyng Henry theyght, and ſo the ſayde lorde Legate doth accept and recogniſe the ſame.</p>
               <p>Where in the parliament begonne and holden at Weſtminſter in the .xxi. yere of the raygne of the late kynge of moſt famous memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry kyng Henry theyght, one act was then and there made agaynſt pluralities of benefices, for takynge of farmes by ſpiritual men and for none reſidence, in the which act amongeſt other thynges it was ordeyned and enacted that yf any perſon or perſons, at any tyme af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter the fyrſt day of Apryll in the yere of our Lord God a thouſand fyue hundred and thirtye contrary to the ſame act, ſhould procure and obteyne at the court of Rome, or els where anye lycence or ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cences, vnion, tolleration, or diſpenſation, to receaue or take anye more benefices with cure, then was limitted and appoynted by the ſame acte, or els at any tyme after the ſayde daye ſhoulde put in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution any ſuch licence, tolleration, or diſpenſation, before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme obteyned contrary to the ſayd acte, that then euerye ſuch perſon or perſons ſo after the ſayd day, ſuyng for himſelfe, or receauynge, &amp; takyng ſuch benefice by force of ſuch lycence or lycences, vnion, tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration, or diſpenſation, that is to ſaye: the ſame perſon or perſons only, and no nother, ſhould for euery ſuch defaulte, incurre the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, payne and penaltie of .xx. li. ſterl. and ſhould alſo loſe the whole profytes of euery ſuch benefice or benefices, as he receaueth, or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb n="xii" facs="tcp:25971:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
by force of any ſuch licence or licences, vnion, tolleration, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>penſation. And where alſo in the ſayd acte it was ordeyned and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted, that yf any perſon or perſons dyd procure, or obteyne at the court of Rome, or els where anye maner of lycence or diſpenſation to be none reſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce at their dignities, prebend, or benefices, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the ſayd acte, that then euerye ſuche perſon or perſons puttynge in execution any ſuche diſpenſation, or licence for him ſelfe from the ſayd fyrſt daye of Apryll, in the ſayde yeare of our Lord God, a M. fyue hundred and thirtye, ſhould runne and encurre in the penalty damage, and payne of .xx. li. ſter. for euery tyme ſo doinge to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feyted and recouered, as by the ſayd act is declared. And yet ſuche licence or diſpenſation ſo procured, or to be put in execution, to bee voyde and of none effecte, as by the ſame acte more playnely it doth and may appeare.</p>
               <p>Be it enacted by thauctoritye of thys preſent parlyament, that aſmuch only of the ſayd act, as concerneth the articles and clauſes aforeſayd, and al and euery the wordes and ſentences conteyned in the ſayd act, concernynge the ſayde articles and clauſes, and euerye of them, ſhal from hence forth be repealed, adnulled, reuoked, adnihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, and vtterly made voyde for euer. Any thyng in the ſayde act to the contrary in any wyſe notwythſtandyng.</p>
               <p>And where alſo at the ſeſſion of the ſame parliament holden vpon prorogation, in the .xxiii. yere of the raygne of the ſayde late kynge Henry theyght. one act intituled: the act that no perſon ſhalbe cited out of the dioceſſe where he or ſhe dwelleth, except in certaine caces And where alſo at the ſayd parliament, in the ſeſſion holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter vpon prorogacion the .xxiiii. yere of the raygne of the ſayde late kyng Henry theyght, one act was made that appeales in ſuche caſes as hath ben vſed to be purſued to the ſea of Rome, ſhould not from hence forth be had nor vſed but within this realme. And wher alſo at the ſayd parliament holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Weſtminſter, in the .xxi. yere of the raygne of the ſayd late kynge Henry the eyght, and there conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued by diuers prorogations vntyl the .xxiiii. daye of Apryll, in the xxvii. yere of hys raigne, one act was made concerning reſtraintes of paymentes of annaties, and firſte fruites of archebyſhopryckes, and byſhopryckes of the Sea of Rome. And where at a Seſſion of the ſayd parlyament, holden in the .xxv. yeare of the raygne of the ſayde late kyng, there was alſo one act made, in tituled, the ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the clergie to the kynges maieſties, and one other act intitu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led, one act reſtraynynge the ſayde paymentes of annates, or fyrſte fruites to the byſhop of Rome, and of the electing and conſecrating of the archbyſhoppes and byſhoppes within thys realme. And one other act was then and there made entituled: an act co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernyng the exoneration of the kynges ſubiectes, from exactions &amp; impoſitions
<pb facs="tcp:25971:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
before that time payed to the Sea of Rome, and for hauing licences and diſpenſations within this realme, withoute ſuynge further for the ſame.</p>
               <p>Be it enacted by thauctorytye of thys preſente parlyament, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſayde ſeuerall actes made for the reſtraynt of payment of the ſayde annates, and fyrſte fruites, and all other the ſayd actes made in the ſayd .xxiiii. and .xxv. yeres of the raygne of the ſayd late kynge, and euery of them and al &amp; euery braunch, article, matter, and ſentence in them, and euery of them conteyned, ſhalbe by auctorytye of thys preſent parliament from hence forth vtterly voyde, made fruſtrate and repealed, to al intentes, conſtructions and purpoſes.</p>
               <p>And be it further enacted by thauctority of thys preſent parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that al and euerye theſe actes folowyng. That is to ſaye: one act made at the ſeſſion of the ſayd parliament holden vpon proroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at Weſt. in the .xxvi. yere of the raygne of the ſayde late kynge Henry theyght, entituled an acte, concerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinges highnes to be ſupreme head of the church of England, and to haue auctorytye to reforme and redreſſe al errours hereſies. &amp; abuſes in the ſame. And one other acte made in the ſame ſeſſion of the ſame parliament entituled: an acte for nomination and conſecration of Suffragans within this realme. And one other acte made in the .xxvii. yeare of the raigne of the ſayd late kyng Henry the eyght, entituled: an acte wherby the kynge ſhoulde haue power to nominate .xxxii. perſons of his Clergy and Lay fee for the makyng of Eccleſiaſtical lawes. And alſo one other act, made at the parliament holden at Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in the .xxviii. yere of the raygne of the ſaid late kyng Henry the eyghte, entituled: an acte extinguiſhynge thauctorytye of the Byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome. And one other act made in the ſame parlyament, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled: an act for the releaſe of ſuche as then had obteyned, preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded licences, and diſpenſations from the Sea of Rome. And alſo al that parte of the acte, made in the ſayde .xxviii. yeare of the ſayde kynge, entituled: an acte for the eſtabliſhement of the Succeſſion of the imperial crowne o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the realme, that concerneth a prohibition to marrye within the degrees expreſſed in the ſayd acte. And alſo one other acte made at the parliamente holden at Weſtminſter, in the xxxi. yeare of the raygne of the ſayde late kynge Henrye the eyght, entituled: an acte auctoryſynge the kynges hyghnes to make byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes by his letters patentes. And one other act made in the ſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the ſame parliament begon in the ſayd .xxx. yare, holden vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prorogation, the .xxxii. yere of the reygne of the ſayde kynge Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the eyghte, entitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed: an acte concerninge precontractes of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryages, and touching degrees of conſanguitie. And one other acte made in the parliament holden at Weſtminſter, in the .xxxv. yere of the reygne of the ſaid late king Henry theyght, entituled: an act for
<pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:25971:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the ratification of the kings maieſties ſtile, ſhal henceforth be repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, made fruſtrate, voyde, and of none effect. And where alſo at the ſaid parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t holden at Weſtminſter in the .xxxv. yere of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> raigne of the ſayd late kyng Henry theyght, one other act was made enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teled: an act concerning theſtabliſhment of the ſucceſſion of the ſayd king in the imperial crowne of this realme. In the which act there is a forme of a corporall othe deuiſed and ſet furth, that euery ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of this realme ſhould be bounde to take againſt the power, auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie and iuriſdiction of the ſea of Rome. Be it enacted by thauc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of this preſent parliament that ſo muche of the ſayd acte as toucheth the ſayd oth agaynſt the ſupremacy, and al othes ther vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on had, made, &amp; geuen ſhalbe from henceforth vtterly voyde, repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and of none effect. And wher alſo one other act was made in the xxxvii. yere of the raigne of the ſayd late king Henry theyght enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled an act that doctours of the cyuyl law, being maried might ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>erciſe eccleſiaſtical iuriſdiction. Be it enacted by thauctority of this preſent parlyament, that the ſayd act laſt before mencioned, and all and euerye braunche, article, ſentence and matter, conteyned in the ſame, ſhal from henceforth be repealed, and vtterly made voyd, and of none effect.</p>
               <p>And where one other act was made at the fyrſt ſeſſion of the par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyament, holden at Weſtminſter, in the fyrſt yere of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> raigne of king Edward the ſyxt, entituled an act for the repeale of certayne Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, concernyng treaſons, fellonies. &amp;c. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whych act amongeſt other thyngs ther is conteined certeyne prouiſions, paynes, penal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyes, and forfeytures for &amp; agaynſt ſuche, as ſhoulde by open prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynges, expres wordes, ſayinges, writyng, pryntyng ouert dede, or act affirme, or ſet furth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the kyng of this realme, for the tyme be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng, is not or ought not to be ſupreame head in earth, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churches of England and Ireland, ne of any of them, or that the byſhoppe of Rome or any other perſon or perſons, other then the kyng of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land for the tyme beyng, is or ought to be ſupreame heade of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame churches, or any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as in the ſame act laſt before reherſed, more at large is conteyned, and may appeare. Be it enacted by auctority of this preſent parlyament, that theſe clauſes before rehearſed, and other of the ſayd act, concerning the ſupremacy, and all and euerye braunche, article, wordes, and ſentence, in the ſame ſoundyng, or te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng to the derogation of the ſupremacy of the Popes holynes, or the ſea of Rome, &amp; al paynes, penalties, &amp; forfeytures, made againſt them that ſhould by any meanes ſet fur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h, or extol the ſaid ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy, ſhalbe from henceforth vtterly boyde and of none effecte.</p>
               <p>And be it further enacted by thauctoryty aforeſayd, that al clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſentences, and articles of euery other ſtatute, or act of Parlya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made ſithence y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſayd .xx. yeare of the raygne of kyng Henry
<pb facs="tcp:25971:17"/>
theyght, agaynſt the ſupreame auctoryty of the Popes holynes, or Sea apoſtolike of Rome, or conteyning any other matter of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame effect only, that is repealed in any of the Statutes aforeſayd, ſhall be alſo by auctoritie here of from henceforth vtterly voyd, fruſtrate and of none effect.</p>
               <p>And where we your moſt humble ſubiectes, the lordes ſpirituall and temporal, and commons in this preſent parliament aſſembled, haue exhibited to your maieſties one other ſupplication in fourme folowynge.</p>
               <p>We the lordes ſpiritual and temporal, and the commons in thys preſent parlyament aſſembled repreſenting the whole body of thys realme, reduced &amp; receaued by your maieſties interceſſion to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie of Chriſtes churche, and the obedience of the Sea apoſtolyke of Rome, &amp; the Popes holynes gouerning the ſame, make moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſuite vnto your maieſties, to be likewiſe meanes &amp; interceſſors that all occaſions of conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion, hatred, grudge, ſuſpition, &amp; trouble both outwardly &amp; inwardlye in mens conſciences, whiche myghte ariſe amongeſt vs, by reaſon of diſobedience, may by auctoritie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Popes holynes, and by miniſtration of the ſame vnto vs, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt reuerend father in god, the lord Cardinal Poole, by diſpenſation to leration or permiſſion reſpectiuely, as the cace ſhal require, be aboli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhed &amp; taken awaye, and by aucthoritye ſufficient theſe artycles fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowyng, and generally al others, when any occaſion ſhal ſo require may be prouyded for, and confyrmed.</p>
               <p>Fyrſt that al by ſhopryckes, c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thedral churches, hoſpitales, colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, ſcholes, and other ſuch foundations now continuing, made by auctoritye of parlyament, or otherwiſe eſtabliſhed, according to the order of the lawes of thys realme, ſithence this ſchiſme may be con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>firmed and continued for euer.</p>
               <p>Item that mariages made <hi>infra gradus prohibitos conſanguinitatis, affinitatis cognatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s ſpiritualis,</hi> or which might be made voyd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>proper impedimentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> publicae honestatis iustitiae,</hi> or for any other cauſe prohibited by the canons onlye maye be confirmed, and children borne of thoſe mariages declared legittimate, ſo as thoſe mariages were made according to the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of the realme for the tyme being, and be not directely againſt the lawes of God, nor in ſuch caſe, as the Sea apoſtolike hath not vſed to diſpence wythal.</p>
               <p>That inſtitutions of benefices, &amp; other promotions eccleſiaſtical and diſpenſations made according to the forme of the act of parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, may be likewiſe confyrmed.</p>
               <p>That all iudiciall proceſſes, made before any ordinaryes of thys realme, or before any delegates vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any apeales, according to thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawes of the realme, may be likewiſe ratified &amp; confirmed, And finally where certayne actes and ſtatutes haue bene made in
<pb n="xvii" facs="tcp:25971:17"/>
the tyme of the lateſciſme, concernyng the lands, and hereditamen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of Archbyſſhoprykes, and Byſſhoprykes, the ſuppreſſion, &amp; dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of monaſteries, Abbeyes, prioryes, chauntries, colleges, &amp; al other the goodes and catteles of religious houſes. Synce y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che tyme, the ryght, and dominion of certayne landes, &amp; heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, goodes, and catteles, belongynge to the ſame, be diſperſed abroade, &amp; come to the handes, and poſſeſſions of diuerſe and ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>drye perſons, who by gyfte, purchaſe, exchaunge, &amp; other meanes accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to the order of the lawes and ſtatutes of this realme, for the tyme beyng, haue the ſame. For the auoydyng of all ſcruples that might grow by any thoccaſions aforeſaid, or by any other waies, or meanes, whatſoeuer: It may pleaſe youre maieſties, to be interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, and mediatours, to the ſayde mooſte reuerend father, Cardy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Pole, that all ſuche cauſes, and quarels as by pretence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd ſciſme, or by any other occaſion, or meane whatſoeuer, might be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the Popes holynes, or Sea Apoſtolyke, or by any other iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diction Eccleſiaſticall, maye be vtterly remoued, and taken away ſo as all perſons hauyng ſufficient conueyaunce of the ſayd lands, and hereditamentes, goodes and cattels, as is aforeſayd, by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon lawes actes, or Statutes of this realme, maye withoute ſcruple of c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſcience, enioye them without impechment or trouble by prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of any generall counſayle, Canons, or Eccleſiaſticall lawes, &amp; cleare from all daungers of the cenſures of the churche.</p>
               <p>And comformably here vnto, the Byſſhoppes and Cleargy of the prouynce of Cantorbury haue preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to your maieſties a ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, in this tenour that foloweth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nos Epiſcopi &amp; Clerus Cantuarienſis prouinciae in hac Synodo more noſtro <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>olito, dum Regni parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> celebratur, congregati, cum omni debita humilitate &amp; reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia, exponimus Maiestatibus ueſtris, quod licet Eccleſiaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quibus in Epiſcopos, Decanos, Archidiaconos, rectores, &amp; uicarios praefecti ſumus, &amp; animaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quae nobis &amp; curae noſtrae ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectae ſunt &amp; earundem bonorum iuriſdictionu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; iurium, ex ſacroru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Canonum diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, defenſores, &amp; curatores co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>stituti ſumus &amp; prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teria ip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rum bona iuriſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>is, &amp; iura in pernicioſo huius Regni prae terito ſciſmate deperdita &amp; amiſſa, omni ſtudio, &amp; totis noſtris uiribus recuperare &amp; ad pristinum Eccleſiarum ius reuocare, iuris remedijs niti deberemus: Nichilominus tamen habito prius per nos ſuper hac re maturo Conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>io, et deliberatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e ingenuèfatemur, nos optimê cognoſſere, quam haec bonor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Eccleſiasticor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> difficilis &amp; quaſi impoſsibiliseſſet recupera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio propter multiplices ac pene inextricabiles ſuper hijs habit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s contrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiones
<pb facs="tcp:25971:18"/>
&amp; quod ſi ea tentaretur, quies et tranquillitas Regni facile per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbaretur, &amp; unitas Eccleſiae Catholicae, quae iam pietate, &amp; aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Maiestatum ueſtrum hoc in regno introducta est, cum maxima dif<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficult ate ſuum debitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> progreſſum, &amp; ſinem ſortiripoſſet. Ideo nos bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; quietem publicam priuatis commoditatibus, &amp; ſalutem totanimaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> praetioſo Christi ſanguine redemptarum terrenis bonis antepone<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, &amp; non quae nostra, ſed quae Ieſu Chriſti ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t quaere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, Maiestates uestras enixe rogamus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> humiliter ſupplicamus, ut reuerendiſſimo in Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to patri, domino Reginaldo Cardinali Polo, adipſas, &amp; uniuerſum hoc Anglie regnum ſanctiſſimi domini nostri, Domini Iulij, Papae tertij, &amp; Apoſtolicae ſedis de latere legato, haec nomine nostro inſinuare, &amp; apud eu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> intercedere digne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur, ut in hiis bonis Eccleſiaſtiſis in parte, uel into toarbitrio ſuo iuxta facultates ſibi ab eodem ſanctiſſimo domino no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stro Papaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceſſas eorundem bonorum detentoribus elargiendis et relax andis publicum bonum priuato pacem et tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quillitatem diſsidijs, &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turbationibus, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> animarum ſalutem bonis terrenis praeferre, &amp; ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponere uelit. Nos enim in omnibus quae ab ipſo legato ſtatuta, et ordina ta circa haec bonafuerint exnunc, prout extunc, et eco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſenſum noſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum preſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>us, imo etiam ut in premiſſis ſe difficilem aut restrictum reddere non uelit, maiestates uestrae nostro nomine eum hortari, &amp; ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gare dignabuntur. Inſuper maiestatibus uestris ſupplicamus ut pro ſua pietate efficere dignentur, ut ea quae adiuriſdictionem nostra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et liberta tem Eccleſiaſticam pertinent, ſine quibus debitum nostri pastoralis of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficij et curae animarum nobis commiſſae exercere non poſſumus, uobis ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>periorum temporum iniuria ablatarestituantur, et ea nobis, et Eccleſij perpetuo illeſ a et ſalua perman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ant, et ut omnes leges, quae hanc noſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iuriſdictionem, &amp; libertatem Eccleſiaſticam tollunt, ſeu quouis modo impediunt, abrogentur ad bonorem dei, et maiestatum uestraru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſi huius Regni Spirituale, et temporale commodum, &amp; ſalutem, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam ſpem etiam habentes, Maiestates uestras, pro ſua ſingulari in ipſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deum pietate, pro<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> multis et inſignibus ab ipſius dei bonitate acceptis beneficijs neceſſitatibus, &amp; in commodis huius ſui Regni Eccleſiarum maximê curam animarum habentium nunqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> defuturas eſſe, ſed prout opus fuerit, conſulturas at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> prouiſuras.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Foraſmuche as the ſayde mooſte reuerende father, the Lord Le<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gate, at the interceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of your maieſties, hath by thauctoritie of the Sea Apoſtolike, ſufficiently diſpenſed in the matters ſpecified in the ſayd ſeueral ſupplications, as in his ſayde letters of diſpenſation is conteyned more at large. The tonor wherof enſueth,</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="xviii" facs="tcp:25971:18"/>
                  <hi>Reginaldus miſeratione diuina Sanctae Mariae in Coſmodin Sanctae Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>manae Eccleſiae, Diaconus, Cardinalis Poluinuncupatus, ad Sereniſſimos Philippum &amp; Mariam, Angli<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Reges, fidei de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſores, et uniuerſum An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gliae regnum, Sanctiſſimi Domini noſtri Papae, et ſede<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Apostolicae de la <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>re legatus eiſdem Sere niſſimis Philippo et Mariae Regibus ſalutem in Domino ſempiternam. Cum ſupremum co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſilium istius Regni parlame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nun cupatum Maiestatibus uestris, per ſuos ſupplices libellos expoſuiſſet quod perniciociſſimo ſciſmate, in hoc regno alias uigente, quod nunc dei miſericordia, &amp; maiestatum ueſtrarum pietate extinctum est, authorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ipſius parlame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti, non nulli Epiſcopatus diuiſi, &amp; ex his aliquae infe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riores Eccleſiae, in cathedrales ere ſtae, et ſcholae, atque hoſpitalia fundata nec non plurimae diſpenſationes et beneficiorum prouiſiones factae fueru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ac multae perſonae quibus perſuaſum fuerat, luris Canonici diſpoſitiones hoc in Regno amplius locum non habere, inter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e in gradibus conſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis uel aſſinitatis de iure prohibitis, &amp; alijs impedimentis Canonicis ſibi obſtantibus matrimonia, per uerba de praeſenti co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>traxerunt, et multis actus iudiciarij, &amp; proceſſus, tam in primis, quam ulterioribus inſtantijs ſuper rebus ſpiritualibus, &amp; Eccleſiaſticis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oram iudicibus tam Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rijs quàm delegatis, qui au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t horitate laicali procedebant, habiti &amp; ſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, ad ſuper eis etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiaelatae, et promulgatae fueru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, et bona eccleſiactica per diuerſas eiuſdem regni perſonas occupata, et apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſa fuerunt. Quae quidem licet ex ſacrorum Canonum inſtitutis irrita deolarari poſſent, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſi ad alium statum, quam in quo nunc ſunt, reuocarentur, publica pax &amp; quies uniuerſi regni turbaretur, et maxima confuſio oriretur, preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim ſi dictorum honorum poſſeſſores molestarentur, et propterea maieſtati busuestris humiliter ſupplicauerint, ut apud nos intercedere dignentur, ut premiſſarum rerum firmitari, et ſtabilitati, et ſimul huius Regni quieti, et tranquillitati de benig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tate Apoctolica prouidere uelimus. Cumque Epiſcopi quoque deinde, ac reliquus prouinciae Cantuarienſis Clerus totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fere corpus Eccleſiasticorum regni repreſentus, ad quos haec bonorum Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiasticorum cauſa maximê pertin et, expoſuerint, quod haec bona ad ius eccleſiarum reuocare non poſſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, quin pax vniuerſalis, &amp; quies huius reg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ni turbetur, et cauſa fidei at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> unitatis Eccleſiae, iam toto omnium conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu hoc in regno introducta, in maximum periculum adducatur, et propte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea ipſi quo que ſupplicauerint, ut apud nos intercedere uelint, ut in his bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nis Eccleſiaſticis poſſeſsoribus relaxandus restricti et difficilis eſse nolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, maiestates autem ueſtrae, ad quas maxime spectat prouidere, ut regnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ipſaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> potestari regimini et curae commiſſum in pace et tranquillitate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruetur.
<pb facs="tcp:25971:19"/>
His ſupplicationibus et postulatis cognitis et mature co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideratis iudicauerit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a omnia, et maxime illa, quae in bonoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eccleſiasticorum cauſa petuntur, pro cauſa fidei et pro pace publica<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> per nos debere ſine ulla dilatio ne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cedi, et que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>admodu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rogatae fueru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, apud nos intercedere dignatae fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint, prout in ſupplicationibus per idem ſupremum conſilium, et epiſcopos ac clerum praefatum maieſtatibus uestris porrectis, atque in libello inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiones per eaſdem maieſtates uestras nobis ſimulcum alijs ſupplicatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus exhibito, latius apparet. Idcirco nos qui ad maiestates uestras, et hoc nobiliſsimum uestrum regnum à Sanctiſſimo Domino noſtro Iulio Pap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tertio ipſius et ſedis Apostolicae de latere legati miſſi ſumus, ut regnum iſtud, quod iamdiù ab Eccleſiae Catholicae unitate ſeparatum fuerat. Deo et Eccleſiae Christi, eiuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in terris u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cario reconciliaremus: et ut ea omnia quae ad pace<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et tranquillitatem huius regni pertinerent, omni ſtudio pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curaremus, postaua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dei benign itate, et maiestatem ueſtrarum pietate, per authoritatem eiuſdem Sanctiſſimi Domini nostri Papae, cuius uices hic ſuſtinemus, reconciliatio iam facta eſt, ut paci et tranquillitati regni prae fati conſulamus, atque ut unitas eccleſiae, ex qua ſalus tot animarum prae cioſo Chriſti ſanguine redemptarum dependet, hoc in regno iam introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta corrobaretur, &amp; ſalua permaneat, cum utriuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> rei stabilitatem in eo maxime conſistere, ſi horum Eccleſiaſticorum bonorum poſſeſſoribus mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtia nulla in feratur quo nimus ea teneant, tot et tam grauia teſtimonia nob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s fidem faciant, et maieſtatum uestrarum interceſſio, quae pro unitate Eccleſiae, et ſedis Apostoliçae auctoritate hoc in regno instauranda tam studioſê, et tam pie elaborarunt, eam quam parest auctoritatem apud no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> habeat, et ut uniuerſum hoc regnum ſedis Apoſtolicae maternam uerê in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgentia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et charitatem ergaſe agnoſcat, et re ipſa experiatur: quoſcun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad quos inſra ſcripta pertinent, à quibuſuis excommunicationis, ſuſpenſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, et interdicti, alijs<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> eccleſiaſticis ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenſiis, ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuris et paenis a iure uel ab homine quauis occaſione uel cauſa latis, ſi quibus quomodolibet innodati exiſtunt, ad effectum praeſentium dum taxat conſequendum harum ſerie abſoluentes, et abſolutos fore cenſentes, aucthoritate Apostolica, per litte ras Sanctiſſimi domini noctri, domini Iulij Papae tertij nobis conceſſa, &amp; quafungimur in hac parte, tenore praeſentium diſpenſamus, quod omnes et ſingulae Cathedralium Eccleſiarumerectiones, hoſpitalium, et ſcholaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, fundationes tempore praeteriti ſciſmatis, licet de facto et nulliter atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tatae ineo ſtatu, in quo nunc ſunt, perpetuo firmae et ſtabiles parmaneant, illiſ que Apostlicae firmitatis robur adijcimus, it a ut non ea aucthoritate, qua prius, ſed ea quam nunc eis tribuimus, factae ab omnibus cenſeantur, &amp; c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="xix" facs="tcp:25971:19"/>
omnibus et ſingulis perſonis regni praedicti, quae in aliquo conſanguinita tis uel affinitatis graduetiam multiplici, uel cognationis ſpiritualie, ſeu publicae honestatis iusticiae impedimento de iure poſitiuo introductis, &amp; in quibus ſanctiſſimus dominus noster Papa diſpenſare conſueu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t matri mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia ſcienter uel ignorantur de facto contraxerint ut alique imped imen torum premiſſorum, non obstante in eorum matrimoniis, ſic contractis li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; licite remanere, ſeu illa de nouo contrahere poſſint, miſericorditer in domino diſpenſamus, prolem ſuſceptam, ſuſcipiendam legitima<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, de cernentes, ita tamen ut qui ſcienter et malitioſe contraxerint, à ſententia exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municationis, et ab inceſtus ſeu ſacreligij reatu, abſolutione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> à ſuo ordi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nario, uel curato, quibus id faciendi facultatem conſedimus, obtineant, ac omnes Eccleſiasticas ſeculares, ſeu quorumuis ordinum regulares perſonas quae aliquas impetrationes, diſpenſationes, conceſſiones, gratias, et indulta tam Ordines, quam beneficia Eccleſiastica, ſeu alias ſpirituales materias praetenſa aucthoritate ſupremitatis Eccleſiae<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Anglicanae licet nulliter, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> de facto obtinuerint, et ad cor reuerſae Eccleſiae unitati restitutae fuerint, in ſuis Ordinibus, &amp; beneficijs per nosipſos, ſeu à nobis ad id deputatos, miſericorditer recipiemus, prout iam multae receptae fuerunt, ſecum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſuper his opportunè in Domina diſpenſabimus: Ac omnes proceſſus inquibuſuis instantijs coram quibuſuis iudicibus, tam ordinariis quam dilig atisetia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> laicis ſuper materijs ſpiritualibus habitos &amp; formatos, &amp; ſententias ſuper eis latas, licet nulliter et de facto, quoad nullitatem ex defectu iuriſdictio nis praefato tantum inſurgentem ſanamus, illoſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>, et illas aucthoritate A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> postolica confirmamus: Ac quibuſuis huius reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ni perſonis, ad quarum ma nus bona Eccleſiaſtica ex quocun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> contractu ſeu titulo onoroſouellucra tiuo iam deuenerint, illaque <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enuerint, ſeu etiam teneant, omnes, &amp; qous cum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fructus ex eiuſde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bonis, licet indebitê perceptos, in totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> remittimus &amp; relaxamus. V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>olentes ac decernentes, quod dictorum bonorum Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asticorum ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mobilium quam immobilium poſſeſſores praefati non poſſiut in preſenti nec in posterum, ſeu per conſiliorum generalium, uel prouin cialium diſpoſitiones, ſeu decretales Romanorum pontificum Epistolas, ſeu aliam quamcun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> cenſuram eccleſiastica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in dictis bonis ſeu eorunde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeſſione molestari, in quietari, uel perturbari, nec eis aliquae ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſurae uel pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae eccleſiasticae propter huiuſmodi detentionem, ſeu non reſtitutione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> irro gari uel infligi, &amp; ſic per quoſcunque iudices, &amp; auditores ſublata eis qua ſuis aliter iudicandi et interpretandi facultate, et auctoritate iudicari et diffiniri debere, &amp; quicquid ſecus attemptari contigerit, irritum et inane fore decernimus, non obſtantibus praemiſsis defectibus, &amp; quibuſuis
<pb facs="tcp:25971:20"/>
Apoſtolicis, ac in prouincialibus, et <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſinodalibus concilijs editis, ſpeciali<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bus uel generalibus conſtitutionis, &amp; ordinationibus, caeteriſque contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rijs quibuſcunque, Admonemus tamen cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m diuiſio Epiſcopatuum, &amp; erec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio Cathedraliu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Eccleſiarum fint de maioribus cauſis, quae ſummo ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiei ſunt reſeruatae, recurrendum eſſe ad ſuam ſanctitatem, &amp; ab ea ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>citer postulandum, ut haec confirmare, ſeu de nouo facere dignetur. Et licet omnes res mobiles Eccleſiarum indiſtincte ijs, qui eostenent relax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auerimus, eos tamen admonit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s eſſe uolumus, ut aut oculos habentes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ui ni iudicij ſeueritatem contra Balthaſarem Regem Babilonis, quiua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa ſacra non à ſe ſed à patre è templo ablata in prophanos uſus conuertit ea proprijs Eccleſijs ſi extant, uel aliis reſtituant. Hortantes etiam, &amp; per uiſer a miſericordiae Iuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Christi obtestantes eos omnes, quos haecres tangit, ut ſalutis ſuae non omnino immemores, hoc ſaltem efficiant, ut ex bonis Eccleſiaſticis, maxime ijs, quae ratione perſonatuum et uicariatuum populi miniſtrorum ſuſtentationi fuerint ſpeſialiter deſtinata, ſeu alijs Ca thedralibus, &amp; alijs quae nunc extant, inferioribus Eccleſijs curam anima rum exercentibus it a prouideatur, ut earum pastores, perſonae et uicarii co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mode, &amp; honeste iuxta eorum qualitatem, &amp; ſtatum ſuſtentari poſſint, &amp; curam an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>marum laudabiliter exercere, &amp; onera incumbentia congruê ſupportare Datum Lambeth prope Londinum VV intonien<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Dioceſſ An<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> no Natiuitatis domini Milleſimo, quingenteſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>o, quinquageſimo quarto Nono Cal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Ianuarii Pontif<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sanctiſsimi in Christo patris, &amp; Domini no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stri, Domini Iuli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, diuina prouidentia Papae tertij. Anno quinto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reginaldus Cardinalis Polus Legatus</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We the ſayd lordes ſpirituall and temporal, and commons in this preſent parliament aſſembled, rendring moſt humble thankes to your maieſtyes, by whoſe interceſſion and meanes we haue obteyned the ſayd dyſpenſations of the popes holynes by the ſayd moſte reuerende father in God, his legate, moſt humbly beſecheth the ſame, that it may be ordeined as foloweth.</p>
               <p>And therfore be it enacted by thauctoritie of thys preſent parliament, that al, &amp; ſinguler articles &amp; clauſes conteined in the ſaid diſpenſation as well touching the eſtablyſhment of Byſſhoprykes, and cathedrall churches, as alſo the confirmation of marriages in degrees prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the canons of the churche, the legittimation of chyldren, and the ratificatyon of proceſſe, and of ſentences in matters eccleſiaſticall, touchyng the inualiditie of them for wante of iuriſdiction, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions and deſtitutions, of, and in benifices and promotyons eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall, diſpenſations, and graces, gyuen by ſuche order, as the pub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>like lawes of the realme then approned, and al other thynges before
<pb n="xx" facs="tcp:25971:20"/>
conteyned in the ſayd letters of dyſpenſations, ſhal remayne &amp; be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted and taken, to all intentes and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtructions in the lawes of this realme, lawfull, good, and effectuall to be alleged and pleaded in all courtes eccleſiaſticall and temporall, for good and ſufficiente matter, eyther for the playntyfe or defendaunt, without any allegation, or ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iection, to be made agaynſt the validitie of them, by pretence of any ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nerall counſayle, canon, or decree, to the contrary made, or to be made in that behalfe.</p>
               <p>And where as diuerſe and ſondrye late Monaſteryes, Pryoryes, Commaundryes, Nonneryes, Deaneries, Prebe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, Colleges, Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitales, Houſes of fryers, Chaunteryes, and other religious and eccle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiaſticall houſes and places, and the manours, graunges, meſuages, landes, tenementes, rectoryes, tythes, pentione, portions, vycareges churches, chappels, aduonſons, nominations patronages, annuities, rentes, reuertions, ſeruyces, and other poſſeſſions, and here ditamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes to the ſayd late monaſteries, priories, nonneries, commaundryes, de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nryes, chauntryes, prebendes, houſes of Fryers, colleges, Hoſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talles, and other religious and eccleſiaſtical houſes and places, and to ſondrye Archebyſſhop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ykes, and Byſſhoprykes within thys realme, late appertaynyng and belongyng, came aſwell to the handes &amp; poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the ſnyd kyng of famous memory Henrye the eyghte, father vnto your maieſtie, our ſayd ſoueraygne Ladye by dyſſolution, gyfte, graunt, ſurrendre, attaynder, or otherwyſe, as alſo to the handes and poſſeſſion of diuers and ſondry other perſones, and bodyes polytyke and corporate, by ſondry meanes, conueyaunces, and aſſuraunces, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to the ordre of the lawes and ſtatutes of thys realme.</p>
               <p>And where alſo diuerſe manours, landes, tenementes, and heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamentes percell of the poſſeſſions of Archbyſſhoprykes and Byſſhop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rykes, and manye and ſondrye late deaneryes, colleges, chauntryes, rectories, Prebendes, Free chappeles, Guyldes, and Fraternytyes, manours, houſes, Graunges, landes, Tenementes, rentes, ſeruyces, and other Eccleſiaſticall poſſeſſions, and hereditamentes, goodes, and catteles to the ſayde Archebyſſhoprykes, Byſſhoprykes, deanries, colleges, chaunteryes, free chappels, tec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oryes guyldes, and fraterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties late appertayning and belongynge or appointinge, to and for the fyndynge ofpryeſtes obyttes, lyghtes or other lyke purpoſe, came as wel to the handes &amp; poſſeſſion of the late noble kyng Edward the ſyxt brother vnto your maieſtie ſeueraygne Lady, by vertue of an acte of parliament thereof made, or otherwiſe, as alſo to the handes and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of diuerſe and ſondry other perſons, and bodies poly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yke and corporate by ſondry meanes, conueyaunces, and aſſuraunces, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ordre of the lawes of this realme: a great nomber of which ſayd late monaſteries priores, nonneries, commaundryes, deaneries, colleges, hoſpytales, prebendes, chaunteryes, free chappeles, guylds,
<pb facs="tcp:25971:21"/>
&amp; fraternities, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mannoures, graunges, meſuages, landes, tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, rentes, reuercions, ſeruyces, tythes, pentions, portions vyca reges, churches, chappeles, aduouſons, nominations, patronages, an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nuities, and hereditamentes, goodes, and cattels, to the ſaid monaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tyes, prioryes, nonneryes, commaundries, deaueries, colleges, hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>talles, chaunteries, fre chappelles, guyldes, fraternities, and other ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rleſiaſticall houſes. Archbyſſhopryckes, and Byſſhoprykes, belonging as well for great ſommes of moneye, as for other good, and reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cauſes, and conſiderations, haue bene conueyed and aſſured to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe the ſubiectes, and bodyes polytyke of thys realme, aſwel by the ſayd kyng Henry theyght, the ſayd kynge Edwarde the ſixte, and by your hyghnes our ſoueraygne Lady, and ioyntly by both youre ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties, as alſo by diuerſe the owners of the ſayd eccleſiaſticall poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whych ſayd conueyaunces, and aſſuraunces by their ſondrye let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters patentes, and other wrytynges more playnely do and maye ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare. Foraſmuch as the ſayd moſt reuerend father hath alſo by the ſayd diſpenſations, remoued and taken away al matter of empeache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, trouble, and daunger, whych by occaſion of any generall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle, canon, or degree eccleſiaſticall myghte touche and diſquiete the poſſeſſions of ſuch goodes moueable, landes, tenementes, poſſeſſyons and hereditamentes, as were of late belongynge to anye of the ſayde Archbyſſhoprykes Byſſhoprykes, monaſteryes, pryoryes, nonneries commaundries, deaneryes, colleges, chauntryes, prebendes, rectory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, hoſpita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, houſes of fryers, or other religious and eccleſyaſticall houſes, and places, of what nature, name, kind, or qualitie ſoeuer they be of. Yet for that the title of al landes, poſſeſſions, and hereditamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in thys your maieſties realme and dominions, is grounded in the lawes, ſtatutes and cuſtomes, of the ſame, and by your highe iuriſdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, aucthoritie royall, and crowne imperiall, and in your courtes on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to be impleaded, ordered, tryed, and iudged, and none otherwyſe, and vnderſtandyng, that the whole ful, and mooſte gratious intentes mynd and determination of your moſt excellente maieſties be, that all and euery perſon and perſones, bodyes polytyke, and corporate, theyr heyres, ſucceſſours, and aſſygnes, and euery of them, ſhall haue, kepe, retayne and enioye all, and euerye their eſtates ryghtes, poſſeſſyons, and intereſtes, that they and euery of them nowe hathe, or hereafter ſhall haue, of, and in all and euery the manoures, graunges, meſuages landes, tenementes, tithes, pentions, portions, aduouſons, nominaty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, patronages, annuities, rentes, reuerſions, ſeruices, hundredes, wapentakes, liberties, fraunchiſes, and other the poſſeſſyyus, and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditamentes of the ſayd monaſteries, abbeyes, pryoryes, nonneries commaundries, deaneries colleges, prebendes, hoſpytales, houſes of fryers, chauntryes, rectoryes, vycareges, churches, chappelles. Arch byſſhoprykes, and Byſſhoprykes, and other religious or eccleſiaſticall
<pb n="xxi" facs="tcp:25971:21"/>
houſes and places, or of any of them within this realme, or the domi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nions of the ſame by ſuch lawes and ſtatutes, as were inforce before the fyrſt daye of this preſent Parliament, and by other lawefull co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyaunce to them thereof made.</p>
               <p>That it may be therfore enacted by thauctoritie of this preſente parliament, that aſwell your maieſtie foueraigne Lady, your heirs and ſucceſſours, as alſo all, and euery other perſon &amp; perſons bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es politike and corporate, their heyres, ſucceſſours, &amp; aſſignes now hauing, or that hereafter ſhall haue, hold or enioye any of the ſcites of the ſayd late monaſteries, and other the religious or eccleſiaſtical houſes or places, and al the ſayd manours graunges, meſuages lan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, tenementes, tithes, pentions, portions, globe landes, aduouſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s nominations, patronages, annuities, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, reuerſions, ſeruices hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dredes, wapentakes liberties, fraunchiſes, profits, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities, and other the poſſeſſions and hereditame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of the ſaid late monaſteries abbeyes, pryories, nonneries, commaundries, deaneries, colleges, prebe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, hoſpitals, houſes offriers, rectories, vicareges chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teris churches, chappels, archbiſhoprikes, biſſhoprikes &amp; other religious &amp; eccleſiaſticall houſes &amp; places, or of anye of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of what name, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or kynde ſoeuer they be, ſhall haue, holde, poſſede, retaine, kepe &amp; enioye all and euery the ſayd ſcites, mannours, graunges, meſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, landes, tenementes, poſſeſſions, profytes, commodities, &amp; other hereditamentes, accordyng to ſuch intereſtes and eſtates, as they and euery of them now haue, or holde, or hereafter ſhal haue or hold of and in the ſame by the dewe ordre and courſe of the lawes &amp; ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of thys realme, whych now<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be, or were ſtandinge in force be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fyrſt day of this preſent Parliament, in maner and fourme, as they ſhoulde haue done, yf this acte had neuer bene had ne made This acte or any thinge herein contayned to the contrarye in anye wyſe notwithſtandyng.</p>
               <p>Sauing to you our ſayde ſoueraygne Lady, your heires and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſours, and euery of them, and to all and euery other perſon &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſubiectes of this realme, and bodyes politike and corporate, &amp; to theyr heires and ſucceſſours, and to the heires and ſucceſſours of all, and euery of them, other then ſuch, whoſe ryght, tytle, or intereſt is bounden, or taken awaye, vndone, or extincte by any acte of parlia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment heretofore made, or otherwiſe al ſuch right, title, clayme, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, intereſtes, rentes, annuities, commodities, commons, offices fees, leaſes, liueryes, lyuynges, pentions, portyons, dettes duties, &amp; other profites, which they, or any of them lawfully haue, or of right ought to haue, or myghte to haue had, in, of, or to any of the premiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or in, of or to any parte. or percell thereof, in ſuch like maner and fourme and condition, to all intentes, reſpectes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> conſtructions, &amp; pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſes, as yf this acte had neuer bene had ne made.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25971:22"/>
And that it maye be further enacted by aucthoritie aforeſayd, that al, and euery article, clauſe, ſenteuce, and prouiſo, conteined, or ſpecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied in any acte, or actes of Parliament, concerning, or touching the aſſuraunce, or conueiaunce of any the ſaid monaſteryes, priories, non neries, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundries, deaneries, prebe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, colleges, chauntryes, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitales, houſes, of fryers, rectories, vicarages, churches, chappeles Archbyſhoprykes, and Byſſhoprykes, and other religious and eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical houſes, and places, or any of them, or in any wyſe concernyng any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>annours, landes, tenementes, profites, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, or other the thynges, before ſpecified to the ſaid king Henry theyght, or kynge Edwarde the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, or either of them, or any other perſon or perſones, or body politike or corporate, and euery of them and all, and euery writinge, dede, and inſtrument, concerning the aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſuraunce of anye the ſame, ſhall ſtande, remayne, and be in as good force, effect, and ſtrength, and ſhalbe pleaded, and taken aduauntage of, to al intentes, conſtructions, and purpoſes, as the ſame ſhoulde, myght, or could haue bene by the lawes and ſtatutes of this realme in caſe this preſent acte had neuer bene had ne made.</p>
               <p>And that al feoffamentes, fynes, ſurrenders, forfaytures, aſſuraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, conueyaunces, eſtates, and intereſtes, in any wyſe conueied, had or made to our ſayd late ſoueraygne lord king Henry theight or to our ſaid late ſoueraigne Lord king Edward the ſixt, or eyther of them, or to any other perſon or perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es, bodies politike or corporate or to any of them by dede or dedes, act or actes of Parliament, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe of any the ſcites, mannours, landes, tenementes, poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s profites, commodities, or hereditamentes of any the ſayd archebiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprikes, Biſſhoprikes, late monaſteries, priories, nonneries com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundries, deaueries, houſes of fryars, colleges, chaunteries, hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talles, prebendes, free chappeles, or of any mannours, landes, tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes reuertions, ſeruices, tithes, pentions, portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, annuities, or of any other hereditamentes, of by, or from any eccleſiaſtical or ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual perſon or perſons, or by, or fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any ſpiritual or eccleſiaſtical cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration, or body politike ſhalbe as good &amp; auailable in the law, to al intentes, conſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; purpoſes, as they were by the lawes &amp; ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of this realme ſtanding in force before the firſt day of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent parliament. And that the ſame may, and ſhalbe pleaded, aleged &amp; take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aduauntage of, in ſuch ſort, and to ſuch effect, as they ſhoulde could, or might haue be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by the lawes and ſtatutes of this realme, ſtanding in force before the ſaid firſt day of this preſent parliament: And that all, and euery clauſe, and article, of ſauing conteined in all and euery the ſayd actes and ſtatutes, ſhall ſtand, remaine, and be in ſuch force, ſtrength, and effecte, as they were before the ſayde fyrſte day of this preſent parliament. Any thynge conteined in this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t acte to the contrary in any wyſe notwithſtanding.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="xxii" facs="tcp:25971:22"/>
And that it maye be in like maner enacted by aucthoritie aforeſaid that whoſoeuer ſhal bi any proceſſe, obteined out of any eccleſiaſtical court within this realme, or without, or by precence of any ſpiritual iuriſdiction, or otherwyſe, contrary to the lawes of this realme in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet or moleſt any perſon or perſones, or bodye politike, for any of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaide manours, landes, tenementes, hereditamentes, or thynges aboue ſpecified, contrary to the wordes, ſentences, and meaninge of this act ſhall incurre the daunger of the acte of preminire, made in the .xvi. yere of kyng Richarde the ſecond, and ſhall ſuffer &amp; incur the forfeytures and paynes, conteined in the ſame.</p>
               <p>Prouyded alway, that it ſhall and may be lefull to anye perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or perſones, body politike and corporate, to ſue in any competent, eccle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiaſtical. or ſpiritual court within this realme, for tythes, rightes, &amp; dueties, that they or any of them ſhall pretend to haue, of, or out of any the ſayd mannours, landes, tenementes, &amp; other the premiſſes and to haue, full and perfect remedy for the ſame, in ſuche maner &amp; fourme, as they or any of them, might, or ought to haue done, or had by the lawes &amp; Statutes of this realme, before the making of this Acte, and as though this act had neuer ben had or made.</p>
               <p>And that it may be further prouided and enacted, bi thauctoritie aforeſayd, that albeit the title or ſtile of ſupremacy, or ſupreame hed of the churche of England and of Irelande, or eyther of them, neuer was, ne coulde be inſtly, or lawefullye attributed or knowledged to any kynge, or Soueraygne gouernoure of this realme, nor in anye wyſe could, or might, ryghtfully, iuſtlye, or lawefully, by any kynge or Soueraigne gouernoure of thys realme, be claymed, chalenged, or vſed. Yet foraſmuch as the ſayd tytle and ſtyle, ſithens the third day of Nouember, in the .xxvi. yeare of the reigne of the ſayd kinge Henry theight, hath bene vſed, and is me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned and conteined in di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uers and fondry wrytes, letters patentes, recordes, exemplificaty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, court rolles, Charters, dedes, inſtrumentes, euidences, bokes and writinges. It ſhalbe lawfull, aſwell to, and for youre maieſties and your ſoueraygne ladies heyres and ſucceſſours, as to, and for euery other perſon, and perſons, and bodies politike &amp; corporate, at all tyme and times hereafter, to haue, retayne, and kepe the ſayde wryttes, letters <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, recordes, exemplifications, court rolles Charters, dedes, inſtrumentes, euidences, bokes, and wrytynges<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and them to ſhewe, exhi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ite, vſe alledge, and pleade, in all tymes &amp; places requiſite or nedefull without any daunger, penaltie, loſſe, for feyture, trouble, ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>peachement for the ſame, any thing in this acte or many other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tes, to the contrary thereof in anywyſe, notwithſtandyng.</p>
               <p>And where your hyghnes Soueraygne Lady<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſynce your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to the crowne of this realme of a good and Chryſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſcience, omit
<pb facs="tcp:25971:23"/>
ted to wryte the ſayd Style of Supremacye, ſpecified in one Act made in the parliament holden at Weſtminſter by prorogatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the xxxv. yeare of the raygne of youre late father king Henry theyghte, aſwell in gyftes, grauntes, letters patentes, as in commiſſions, and other wrytinges, and alſo other haue in theyr wrytynges done the ſame aſwell in your tyme as before. And foraſmuch as notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng any lawe made concernyng the ſayde Style of Supremacye, it was in the free choyſe, libertie, and pleaſure of the kynge of thys realme, and of your hyghnes, whether ye woulde expreſſe the ſame in the ſayde Style or not.</p>
               <p>Be it therefore declared and enacted by aucthoritie of this preſent parliament, that all grauntes, letters patentes, commiſſions indite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>entes, recordes, and writinges, made in youre oure Soueraygne Ladyes name, or in the names of yours Soueraygne Lord &amp; La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, or any other, wherein the ſayd Style of Supremacy is omitted is, and ſhalbe, to all intentes and purpoſes, as good and effectual, as y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſame had bene therein expreſſed, &amp; may be deteined, kept, plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded, and alleged, without any daunger, paine, penaltie, or forfaiture to enſue to any perſon or perſons, or body politike, for or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerninge the omiſſion of the ſame Style, or any parte therof, in any ſuch wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges, &amp; that no perſon ne perſons, ſhalbe impeached, moleſted, or dampnyfyed, for or by reaſon of any ſuch omiſſion.</p>
               <p>And where in an acte of parliament made ſince the ſayd .xx. yere of Kyng Henry theyght, all Bulles, diſpenſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tions, and writynges which were before that time optained from the Sea of Rome, ſhuld be voyde, abolyſhed, and extinguiſhed, with a clauſe, neuertheles y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the matter of them, by vertue of letters patentes from the king the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beyng ſhould, and myght be alleged, pleeded, and allowed, as if the ſame had not bene ſo abolyſhed or extinguyſhed. Foraſmuche as the ſayd Acte is here before amongeſt other repealed and made voyde.</p>
               <p>Be it therefore enacted by aucthoritie of this preſent parliamente that all Bulles, diſpenſations, and priuileges, obteyned before the ſayde .xx. yeare, or at any tyme ſythence, or whych ſhal hereafter be opteined of the Sea of Rome, not conteining matter contrarye or preiudicial to the aucthoritie, dignitie, or preheminence Royal, or imperiall of the realme, or to the lawes of this realme, now being in force, and not in this parliament repealed, may be put in executyon, vſed and alleged in anye courte within this realme, or elles where whether the ſame remayne yet hole, or can appeare to haue bene ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled, in as vayleable and effectuall maner, to all intents, &amp; purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as yf the ſayd Acte had neuer bene had or made. Anye obiection by pretence of extinguyſhment, or ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cellyng of the ſayde Bulles, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations, or priuileges, or of any other matter or cauſe, by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tente of the lawes of this realme, whatſoeuer in any wyſe notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="xxiii" facs="tcp:25971:23"/>
And wher as by diſſolution of monaſteries, and other religious houſes, certayne paryſhe churches and chappeles which wer before exempte, from the iuriſdiction of the Archbyſhop and byſhop of the dioceſſe, and by ſpeciall exemption and priuelege from Rome, were vnder the gouernement and order of the Abbotes, and Prioures of thoſe religious houſes, whych ſayde churches, by colour of the ſayd exemptions, be nowe of ſpeciall graunt from Kyng Henry, &amp; kynge Edwarde, vnder the rule and gouernement, and iuriſdiction of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall and laye men, who can no more enioye, that ſupremacye, ouer thoſe particuler churches, then the king might ouer the hole realme</p>
               <p>Be it therefore enacted, that all Archbyſhoppes, &amp; byſhopes in their dioces, and all other ſpirituall perſon and perſones, hauynge iuriſdiction, and their miniſters and offycers, and no laye perſon, or perſones in euery Churche and place, within the precincte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, beyng exempt, or not exempte, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aye freely, and without impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t execute their ſpirituall iuriſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in al pointes &amp; articles, as though no ſuch exemption or graunt had neuer bene made.</p>
               <p>Prouyded alwaye, and be it enacted, that this act extend not to take awaye, or diminyſhe the priueleges of the vniuerſitie of Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brydge and Oxforde, ne the priuileges, or prerogatiues graunted heretofore to the churches of Weſtminſter, and Wyndeſore, ne the Tower of London, ne preiudiciall, to ſuche temporall Lordes and poſſeſſioners in this realme, as by auncient cuſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> haue enioyed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate of Teſtamentes, of their tenauntes or other.</p>
               <p>And foraſmuch, as after this reconſiliation, and vnitie of this no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble realme, to the body of Chriſtes church, it is to be truſted, that by the aboundaunce of Goddes mercy, and grace, deuotion ſhal encreſe and growe in the hartes of many Subiects of this realme, with de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſire to gyue &amp; beſtow their worldly poſſeſſions, for the reſuſcitating of almoſe, prayer, and example of good lyfe in this realme, to thinte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſuch godly motions and purpoſes ſhould be aduaunced.</p>
               <p>Be it therefore enacted by the aucthoritie of this preſent parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that it ſhalbe lawefull to ſuche as ſhalbe ſeſſed of any manours, la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds tenementes, perſonages tithes, pencions, portions, or other heredi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, whatſoeuer in fee ſymple, in poſſeſſion, reuertio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or remayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, in their owne ryghtes, not beyng coppy hold, may therof make feoffamentes, grauntes, or any other aſſuraunces, or by his laſt will and Teſtament, in wryting, may be queath and geue in fe ſymple, al and euery the ſayd manours, la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, tenementes perſonages, tithes pencions, portions, or other hereditamentes, to any ſpirituall body politike, or corporate in this realme or dominions of the ſame, nowe erected or founded, or hereafter to be erected or founded: withoute any lycence of mortmayne therein to be opteyned: or any wrytte of
<pb facs="tcp:25971:24"/>
                  <hi>ad quod dampnum</hi> to be ſued out for the ſame, the actes <hi>de terri ad manum mortuam non ponendis,</hi> or any other acte or ſtatute, heretofore had or made in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</p>
               <p>Sauyng to the Lordes of the fee, all rentes, ſeruices, dew, or go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng out of any of the ſayd land or tenements, or hereditaments, ſo to be amortized, as is aforeſayd.</p>
               <p>Prouyded alway, that this clauſe of this acte, for geuing the liber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie of, or for the amortezing of landes or tenementes, ſhall continue for, and duryng the ſpace of .xx. yeares nexte, and immediatelye fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowyng, and no lenger.</p>
               <p>And foraſmuch as we your maieſties humble and obedient ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, the lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and commons in this pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent Parliament aſſembled, neither by the making; or deliuering of either the ſupplications aforeſayde, nor by any claufe, article or ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence thereof, or of any other clauſe article or ſentence of this, or any other Statute, or any of the pream<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es of the ſame, made, or agreed vpon in this ſeſſion of this preſent parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, by any maner of inter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pretation, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtruction, implication or otherwiſe intende to derogate empaire, or diminiſhe any of the prerogatiues, liberties, fraunchiſies preheminences, or iuriſdictions of your Croune Imperiall of thys realme, and other the dominious to the ſame belonging, we do moſt humbly beſech your maieſties, that it maye be declared, and ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and be it enacted and declared by aucthoritie of this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, that neither the makyng, exhibiting, or inſertinge in thys preſent ſtatute, or in the preambles of the ſame, of the ſupplications or promys aforeſayd, or either of them, nor any other thing or thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, wordes, ſentences, clauſes, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rticles in the preambles or body of the actes, aforeſayde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhal be conſtrued vnderſtanded or expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to derogat, diminiſhe or take away any the liberties<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> priuileges, pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rogatiues, preheminences, auctorities, or iuriſdictions, or any parte or percel therof, which were in your imperial croune of this realme, or dyd belong to your ſaid imperiall croune the twenty yeare of the reigne of yours the Quenes maieſties moſte noble father, or anye other your moſt noble progenitours, before the ſayd twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tye yere, &amp; the popes holines, and Sea Apoſtolike, to be reſtored, and to haue and enioye ſuch aucthoritie, preheminence, and iuriſdiction as hys holines, vſed, and exerciſed, or myght lawfully haue vſed and exerci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed biaucthoritie of his ſupremacie, the ſaid twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie yere of the reign of the kynge your father, within this your realme of Englande, and other your Dominions, without diminution, or enlargement of the ſame, and none other. And the Eccleſiaſticall iuriſdiction of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chebyſhoppes, Biſhoppes, and ordinaries, to be in the ſame ſtate, for proceſſe of ſuites, punyſhment of crimes, and execution of cenſures of the churche, wyth knowledge of cauſes belongyng to the ſame, &amp;
<pb n="xxiiii" facs="tcp:25971:24"/>
as large in theſe poyntes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as the ſayd iuriſdiction was the ſayde .xx. yeare.</p>
               <p>Prouyded alwayes, and be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayd, that in and vpon euery ſuch gyftes and deuyſes, to be made to ſuch ſpirituall corporations, or perſones as is aforeſaid, the donor feof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, or diuiſor thereof may reſerue to hym<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and to his heires for euer, a tenure in franke almaine, or a tenure by diuine ſeruice: &amp; to haue all remedies and actions, for and vpon the ſayde gyftes, or deuyſes, and tenures in lyke maner &amp; forme, as was vſed before the eſtatute of Weſtminſter thyrd (commonlye called) <hi>Quia emptores terrarum.</hi> The ſayde eſtatute or any other lawe or cuſtome nowe beyng to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary in any wyſe notwithſtandyng.</p>
               <p>Prouyded alwayes and be it enacted, that all and euery perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; perſones, and bodyes politike and corporate whyche nowe haue or hereafter ſhall haue any eſtate of enheritaunce, freholde, terme, or in treſt, of, in, or to any portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, pention, tithes, glebelandes, or other ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall or ſpirituall profytte, whyche by this acte, and lettres of diſpenſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rehearſed in the ſame, be permitted &amp; ſuffred to remaine and continue in laye mens poſſeſſions, ſhall and may haue like reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye for the recououery of the ſame, and euery parte thereof as they and euery of them myght haue had before the fyrſte day of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parlyament. Any thynge in this acte conteyned to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in any wyſe notwithſtanding.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ An Acte for the puniſhment of traiterous wordes agaynſt the Quenes maieſtie. ¶ The .ix. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as now of late diuerſe noughty ſedicious malicious, &amp; heretical perſons, not hauing the fere of god before their eies, but in a deuilliſhe ſort, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the duetie of their allegiau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregregated the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues together in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenticles, in diuerſe &amp; ſondr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> propha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e places with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this citie of Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſteming the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes to be in the true faith, wher in dede they are in errours &amp; here ſies, &amp; oute of the true trade of Chryſtes catholike religion, &amp; in the ſame places at ſeuerall tymes, vſing theyr phantaſticall and ſciſmati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>call ſeruices, lately taken awaye, and abolyſhed by aucthoritie of par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyament, haue of theyr moſt malicious &amp; cankerde ſtomakes, praied agaynſt the Quenes maieſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie, that God would turne her hert from Idolatrye to the true fayth, or ells to ſhorten her dayes, or take her quickely out of the waye, whyche prayer was neuer harde nor rede to haue ben vſed by anye good Chryſtian manne, agaynſte anye
<pb facs="tcp:25971:25"/>
Prynce though he were a pagan, and infidele, and much leſſe againſt any chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Prynce, and eſpecially ſo vertuous a Princes, as our ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueraygne Lady that nowe is knowen to be, whoſe faithe is and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes hath bene moſt true and catholique, and conſonaunt &amp; agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Chryſtes catholique church, throughout the worlde diſper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
               <p>For reformation whereof, be it enacted by thauctoritie of this pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent parliament, that euery ſuch perſon and perſones, whych ſence y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> begynnyng of this preſent parliament, haue by expreſſe words and ſayinges, prayed, required, or deſyred, as is aforeſayd, or hereafter ſhall praye, by expreſſe wordes or ſayinges, that God ſhould ſhorten her dayes, or take her out of the way (whoſe lyfe almighty god lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge preſerue) or any ſuch lyke malicious prayer, amounting to the ſame effecte, their procurers and abbettours therin, ſhalbe taken, reputed and iudged traytours, and euery ſuch praying, requiring, or deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng ſhalbe iudged, taken, and reputed hygh treaſon, and the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours therin, their procurers and abbettours, beyng therof lauful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conuicte, accordyng to the lawes of this realme, ſhall haue, ſuffer and forfeyte, as in caſes of high treaſon.</p>
               <p>¶ Prouyded alway and be it enacted, that yf any perſon or perſons ſhall be indicted for any the offences aforeſayde, done and perpetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted duryng this ſeſſion of this preſent parliament, and vpon hys or their arreignement, ſhal ſhewe him or themſelues penitent for ther offence, and ſubmitte him or them ſelues to the kyng and Quenes mercy, and humbly deſyre the ſame, before ſuch Iuſtices or commiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſioners, before whom he or they ſhalbe arraygned, that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of conuiction or attayndour of treaſon, ſhalbe gyuen agaynſte any ſuch perſon or perſones, ſo beyng penitent, and ſubmittinge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues, as is aforeſayd. And in euery ſuch caſe, the iuſtices or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners, before whome ſuch perſon or perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſhalbe arraygned, ſhall haue aucthoritie by vertue of this acte, to preſcribe, adindge, &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynte, ſuch corporall puniſhment, other then death, to ſuch offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der and offenders, as to them by their diſcretion ſhall ſeme conuenient, and vpon that penaunce preſcribed and done, to be diſcharged of the ſayde treaſon, compriſed in that inditement.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ An acte wherby certayne offences be made treaſons, and alſo for the gouernement of the kynges and quenes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties iſſue. ¶ The .x. Chapyter.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="xxv" facs="tcp:25971:25"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as the greate mercy &amp; clemency hereto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore declared bi the y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Quenes highnes, in releaſing the penal lawes, made by her progenitours, hath gi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to many cankarde &amp; traiterous harts to ymagine, practyſe, &amp; attempte things, ſtirring y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple to diſobedience, &amp; rebellion againſt her highnes common polecy, and duetie of ſubiectes, require that ſome lawe be eftſones eſtablyſhed to reſtrayne the malyce of ſuche wycked &amp; euill doers, wherby they may be prehibited to blowe abrode ſuch ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſlaunders and lyes, as they daylye inuente and imagine of her highnes and the kynges maieſtie her mooſte lawefull huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, which when they be hard can not be but odible, and deteſted of all good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſyderyng they touche their maieſties, vpon whome dependeth the whole vn itie, and vniuerſall welth of this realme.</p>
               <p>In conſideration whereof be it ordeined and enacted by the king and the quenes maieſties, with thaſſente of the lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and of the commons in this preſent parliament aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled and by the auctoritie of the ſame, that if any perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or perſons after the firſt day of February next to come during the mariage betwene the king, &amp; the quenes maieſties, do compaſſe or imagine to depriue the kinges maieſtie, that nowe is, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hauing &amp; inioyning ioynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly together with the quenes hyghnes the ſtile, honour, and kinglye name of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> realmes and dominions vnto our ſayd ſoueraygne Lady the quenes highnes appertaining, or to deſtroie the kyng that now is, duryng the ſayd matrimonye, or to deſtroye the quenes maieſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that nowe is, or the heires of her bodye begotten, beynge kinges or Queenes of this Realme, or to leauye warre within thys Realme of England, or within any of the marches of the ſame, agaynſte the kynges maieſtie, that nowe is, duryng the ſayd mariage or againſt the quenes maieſtie that nowe is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or any of her ſayde heyres, beyng kynges or quenes of this Realme, or to depoſe the quenes maieſtie that nowe is, or the heires of her body begotten, beynge kynges or quenes of this realme, from the Imperiall croune of the Realmes and dominions aboueſayd. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame compaſſes, or imaginations or any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maliciouſly, aduiſedly, and directly, ſhall, or do vtter by open preachyng, expreſſe wordes, or ſayings or if any perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones after the ſayde fyrſt day of February by preching expreſſe wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des or ſayinges, ſhall maliciouſly, aduiſedly, and directlye, ſaye pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhe, declare, maintaine or hold opinion, that the kynges maieſtye, that now is duryng the ſaid matrimony, ought not to haue or inioy ioyntlye together with the queenes maieſtie, the ſtile, honoure, and kyngly name of this realme, or that any perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or perſons, being nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the kyng or the queenes maieſties that nowe are duryng the ſayd matrimony betwene them, ought to haue or enioy the ſtile, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure,
<pb facs="tcp:25971:26"/>
and kyngelye name of this realme, or that the Queenes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, that nowe is, duryng her life, is not, or of right ought not to be quene of this realme, or after her death, that the heires of her high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes body beyng kyngs or quenes of this realme of right ought not to be kynges or quenes of this realme, or to haue and enioye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame or that any perſon or perſons, other then the quenes maieſtie, that now is during her life, ought to be quene of this realme, or after her death other then the hetres of her body beyng kinges or queenes of this realme, as long as any of her ſaid heyres of her body begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhalbe in lyfe, or ryght ought to haue and enioy the imperial crowne of this realme. That then euery ſuch offendour, beyng there of duly conuicted, or attainted bi the lawes of this realme, their abbettours procurers, and counſailours, and all, and euerye their comforters, kno wynge the ſayde offences, or anye of theym to bee done, and be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng thereof conuicted or attaynded, as is aboueſaid, for his or their ſuch offence, ſhall forfeite and loſe to the quenes highnes, her heires and ſucceſſours, all his and their goodes, and cattels, and the whole iſſues and proffytes of his and their landes, tenementes, and other hereditamentes, for terme of the lyfe of euery ſuch offendoure or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendours, and alſo ſhall haue, and ſuffer, during his &amp; their liues per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>petual impriſonment.</p>
               <p>Prouyded alwayes and be it enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayde that all and euery eccleſiaſticall perſon being conuicted or attainted in fourme aforeſaid, for euery ſuch his offence, ſhalbe depriued by the ordinary from his promotion ſpirituall or eccleſiaſticall, in ſuch like maner and fourme, that it ſhalbe laweful for euery patron, fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der or giuer thereof, to preſent, after ſuche depriuation had, ſome one other to the ſame, as though the ſayd offendoure or offendours, were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſed. And if any perſon or perſons beyng hereafter conuicted, or at<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taynted of any the ſayde offences, in fourme aforeſayd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted ſhal after his or their conuiction, or attainder, eftſones commit or perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate any of the ſayd offences, in forme aforeſayd. That then euerye ſuch ſeconde offence or offences ſhalbe demed, and adiudged hyghe treaſon, and the offendour or offendours therein, their abbettoures procurers, and councelloures, and al, and euery theyr aidours &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forters, knowing the ſayd offenſes, or anye of them to be done, beyng thereof conuicted or attainted, accordyng to the lawes and ſtatutes of this realme, ſhalbe iudged and demed hyghe traytours, and ſhall ſuffer paynes of deathe, and loſe and forfeyte all their goodes, &amp; cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels landes, and tenementes, to the quenes maieſtie, her heires and ſucceſſours, as in caſes of high treaſon, by the lawes of this realme at this day, of ryght ought to be loſt and forfeyted.</p>
               <p>And be it further enacted by the ſaid aucthoritie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if any perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or perſones at any time after the ſaid firſt dai of February next to come
<pb n="xxvi" facs="tcp:25971:26"/>
duryng the ſayd marriage, compaſſe, or ymagine the death of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges maieſtie, that nowe is, and the ſame maliciouſly, aduiſedly &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly ſhall vtter and attempte by any writing, printing, ouert dede or acte, or yf any perſon or perſons at any time after the ſaid firſt dai of February next comming, ſhall maliciouſly, aduiſedly, and directly by writing, printing, ouert dede, or act, affirme that the kynges ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, that now is, duryng the ſaid matrimony, ought not to haue or enioye ioyntly togethers with the quenes hyghnes, the ſtile, honor and kyngly name of this realme, or that any perſon or perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, being neither the kyng, or the Quenes maieſtie, that nowe is, duryng the ſayd matrimony betwene them ought to haue and enioy the ſtile ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour, and kyngly name of this realme. Or yf any perſon or perſons, after the ſayde day by any writing, printing, ouert dede, or act, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly, aduiſedly, and directly, do affirme, that the quenes maieſtie that nowe is, duryng her lyfe is not, or ought not to be quene of this realme, or after her death, that the heires of her highnes body being kynges<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or quenes of this realme<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of ryght ought not to haue and en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ioye the imperiall Crowne of this realme, or that any perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſones other then the quenes maieſtie that nowe is, duryng her lyfe or after her death, other the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the heyres of her body begotten, being kynges or quenes of this realme, as longe as any of her ſayd heires of her body ſhalbe in lyfe, of ryght ought to haue and enioye the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall crowne of this realme. That then euery ſuch offence and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences ſhalbe adiudged hygh treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; the offender &amp; offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders there in, theyr abbettours, procurers, &amp; cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cellers, and al and euery their ayvours, and comforters, knowyng the ſayd offences, or any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be done, beyng thereof conuicted, or attaynted by the lawes &amp; ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of this realme, ſhalbe demed and adiudged high traytoures &amp; ſhall ſuffer paynes of death, and looſe and forfeyte al their goodes &amp; catteles, landes, and tenementes to the Quenes maieſtie, her heires and ſucceſſours as in caſes of high treaſon, as is aboueſayd.</p>
               <p>And albeit we the lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in this preſent parliament aſſembled, haue firme hope and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in the goodnes of Almyghty god, that like as he hath hether to miraculouſly preſerued the quenes maieſty from many greate &amp; imminent periles &amp; dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, euen ſo he wyll of his infinite goodnes gyue her highnes ſtrength, the rather by our continuall prayers to paſſe well the daunger of deliueraunce of chylde wherwith it hathe pleaſed hym<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (to all our great comfortes) to bleſſe her. Yet foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as all thynges of this worlde be vncertayne, and hauynge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes the dolorus experience of the inconſtant gouerneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t duryng the tyme of the reigne of the late kyng Edwarde the ſyxte, do playnely ſe the manifolde inconueniences, greate daungers, and peryls, that may enſue to this hole realme, yf foreſyghte be not vſed
<pb facs="tcp:25971:27"/>
to preuent euyll chaunces, yf they ſhould happen. For the eſchewing whereof, we the Lordes ſpirituall and temporal, and the commons in this preſent parliament aſſembled for &amp; in conſideration of a moſt ſpecial truſt and confidence, that we haue &amp; repoſe in the kinges ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, for and concernyng the good and politike gouerneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ordre, and adminiſtration of this realme in the tyme of the yonge yers of the iſſue or iſſues of her maieſties body to be borne, if it ſhould pleaſe God to call the quenes highnes out of this preſent lyfe duryng the tender yeares of ſuch iſſue or iſſues (whych God forbyde) according to ſuch ordre and maner as hereafter in this preſent acte, his high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes moſt gratious pleaſure is ſhould be declared and ſet forth, haue made our moſt humble ſuete by thaſſent of the quenes highnes that his maieſtie would vouchſafe to accepte and take vpon him the rule ordre, education, and gouernement of the ſayd iſſue or iſſues to bee borne, as is aforeſayd, vpon which our ſuit being of his ſaid maieſtie moſt graciouſly accepted. It hath pleaſed his highnes not onely to declare, that like as for the fyrſt part his maieſtie verely truſteth, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> almighty God, who hath hetherto preſerued the quenes maieſtie, to giue this realme ſo good an hope of certayne ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blud roial of the ſame realme, wil aſſeſt her highnes with his graces &amp; benedic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions to ſee the frute of her bodye wel broughte forth lyue, and able to gouerne, where of nether all this realme ne al the world beſides ſhold or coulde receaue more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte, then his maieſtie ſhuld &amp; wold. Yet yf ſuch chaunce ſhuld happen, his maieſtie at our humble deſirs is pleaſed and contented, not alonely to except and take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cure and charg of the education, rule, ordre, and gouerneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ſuch iſſues, as of this moſt happy mariage ſhalbe borne betwene the que<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes highnes and him, but alſo during the time of ſuch gouernment, wold by alwayes and meanes ſtudy, trauayle and employe himſelfe to aduaunce the weale, bothe publique and priuate of this realme, &amp; dominions there vnto belongyng, accordyng to the ſaid truſt in his maieſtie repoſed, with no leſſe good wyll and affection, then yf hys hyghnes had byn naturally borne amongeſt vs.</p>
               <p>In conſideration wherof be ir enacted by the kyng and the quee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes moſt excellent maieſties, by thaſſente of the Lordes ſpirituall &amp; temporall, and the commons of this preſent Parliament aſſembled, and by thauctoritie of the ſame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that yf it ſhal ſo pleaſe God, to call the quenes maieſtie out of this preſent lyfe, which god forbydde, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the iſſue of her body, inheritable to the crowne of this realme if it be male ſhal accompliſhe the age of .xviii. yeares, or if it be female, before it ſhalbe of the age of .xv. yeares, and not maryed after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> age of conſent, and before the ſayd age of .xv. yeares. That then &amp; imme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dialy after, and from the deceaſſe of our ſayd Soueraygne Lady y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quene, the kinges maieſtie that now is, ſhall haue the rule, order, edu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="xxvii" facs="tcp:25971:27"/>
and gouernemente of the perſon of ſuche iſſue, or iſſues, and the rule, ordre, and gouernement (vnder ſuche iſſue, or iſſues) of thys realme, and the dominions to the ſame belongyng, vntyl the ſame iſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſue or iſſues, inheritable to the imperial croune of this realme, yf it bee male, ſhall accomplyſhe the full age of eightene yeares and if it be female, vntyll ſuch iſſue female, ſhall accomplyſhe the age of fiuetene yeares, and be maried after the age of conſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and before the ſaid age of fiuetene yeares, if the ſayd iſſue or iſſues, &amp; oure ſayd ſoueraigne Lord the kyng, ſhall ſo longe liue together, and that durynge, &amp; by all the tyme of ſuch gouernement, all, and euerye the pactes, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauntes, articles, and agrementes, mencioned and compriſed in the treatiſes, and act of Parliament, and euery of them made, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, for and concernyng the honourable mariage, had and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mate, betwene the Kyng and Quenes Mateſties which on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of his Maieſtie, bene to be obſerued, perfourmed &amp; kepte, ſhal after the deceaſſe of the Quenes Maieſtie, durynge the time of the ſayd gouernement, remaine, continue, and be in as good, &amp; ful force ſtrength, and effecte, to all intentes, and purpoſes, as they were at any tyme, duryng the ſayde Mariage, or nowe bene, as if they were newly by apte wordes, termes, and ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, inſerted and reherſed in this preſent Acte, and newly made and enacted, to ſtand, remaine continue, and to be obſerued, and kept, durynge the tyme of the ſaid gouernement, and ſhalbe by his Maieſtie, duryng the ſayde time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiolably obſerued perfourmed, mainteined, and vpholden, in ſuche ſorte, and in as full large, and ample maner, to all reſpectes, as they ſhould, and ought to be, duryng the tyme of the ſayde mariage, or af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, and his highnes, and the Quenes moſt excellent Maieſtie, are pleaſed and contented, that it be enacted by this preſent Parliament that nothynge ſhalbe done permitted, or aſſented vnto by his Maie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ieſtie to the contrary.</p>
               <p>And be it further enacted, by the aucthoritie aforeſayd, that if any perſon or perſones, duryng the tyme that our ſayd ſoueraigne lord the kyng that nowe is, ſhall, and ought to haue the ordre, rule, educa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion, &amp; gouernement of ſuch iſſue, or iſſues, beyng kynge or Queene of thys realme, accordyng to the ordre and prouiſion aforeſayd mali<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciouſly, aduiſedly, and directely, biwritynge, prynting, ouert dede or acte dooe compaſſe, attempte, and go aboute to deſtroye the perſon of our ſaid ſoueraygne lorde, or do depriue, or remoue his ſayd high<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes from the order, rule education, and gouernemente of the ſame iſſue, or iſſues, beyng Kyng or quene of this realme, contrary to the tenoure, entent, and true meaning of this preſent acte, that then eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry ſuch perſon or perſones ſo offendyng, their procurers and abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, beyng thereof lawfully conuicte or attainted by the lawes of this realme, ſhalbe demed and adiudged high Traitours: And that
<pb facs="tcp:25971:28"/>
all and euery ſuch offence and offences, ſhalbe demed and adiudged hygh treaſon, And the offendour and offendours therein, their pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>curers, counſaylours, and abbettours, ſhall incure the dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feytures, and penalties of hygh treaſon.</p>
               <p>And be it further enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayd that al trials hereafter to be had, awarded, or made, for any treaſon, ſhalbe had, &amp; vſed onely, according to the due order &amp; courſe of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon lawes of this realme, and not otherwyſe. Sauynge to euery perſon &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſones, bodyes poytyke and corporate, their heires, and ſucceſſours other then the offendours, and their heires and ſuch perſon &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones, as clayme to any of their vſes, al ſuch ryghtes, titles, intereſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, poſſeſſions, leaſſes, rentes, reuertions, offyces, &amp; other profites, whych they or any of them ſhall haue at the daye of the committing ſuch treaſones, or at any tyme afore, in as large &amp; ample maner, as if this acte had neuer bene had nor made.</p>
               <p>Prouyded alwayes, and be it declared and enacted by thauctori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie aforeſayde, that conceylement, or kepyng ſecret of any high tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, be demed and taken onely, miſpriſyon of treaſon &amp; the offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders therein to forfeite and ſuffer, as in caſes of miſpriſion of treaſon hath heretofore bene vſed. Any thynge aboue mencioned, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrarye notwithſtandyng.</p>
               <p>Prouyded alſo, that yf it ſhall fortune hereafter any of the peares of this realme, to be indicted of any of the offences made treaſon or mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpriſion of treaſon by thys acte, that then the ſame pares, or peare, ſo beyng indicted, ſhalbe put to aunſwere vnto euery ſuche endicte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, before the high ſtewarde of Englande for the tyme beyng and to haue his and their triall by his and their peares, and to receaue and haue ſuch like iudgement vpon the ſame tryal of his or their pea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res, or making open confeſſion of the ſame offence, or offences as is vſed in other caſes of hygh treaſon.</p>
               <p>And it is further enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayde, that no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſones ſhall in any wyſe be impeched for any of the offences aboueſayde, committed onely by open preachyng or wordes, onleſſe the offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der or offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders be therefore indicted within ſyxe monethes, next after the ſame open preachyng or wordes. Any thing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teined in this acte to the contrary notwithſtandyng.</p>
               <p>Prouyded alwayes, and be it enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayde that vpon the arraygnement of any perſon, whych hereafter ſhal for tune to be arraygned for any treaſon, mentioned in this act, all and euery ſuch perſon &amp; perſones, or two of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the leaſt, as ſhal here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after wryte, declare, confeſſe, or depoſe any thing or things againſt the perſon to be arraygned, ſhal, yf they be then liuing, &amp; within the realme be brought forth in perſon before the partie arraygned, if he requyre the ſame, and obiecte, and ſaye openly in his hearing what
<pb n="xxviii" facs="tcp:25971:28"/>
they or any of them can agaynſt him, for or con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ernyng any the trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſones, conteined in the indictment, whervpon the partie ſhalbe ſo a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rayg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, onleſſe the partie arraygned for any ſuch treaſon, ſhal wil lyngly confeſſe the ſame at the time of his or their arraygnement.</p>
               <p>Prouided neuertheleſſe, &amp; be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſaid that in al caſes of high treaſon, concernynge coyne curraunt within this realme, or for counterfeytyng the king or Quenes ſygnet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie ſeale, great ſeale, or ſygne manuel, ſuch maner of tryal, and none other be obſerued and kept, as heretofore hath bene vſed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon lawes of this realme. Any lawe ſtatute, or any other thinge or thynges to the contrary notwithſtandyng.</p>
               <p>Prouyded alwayes, that the councellours, procurers, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forters, and abbettours for his or their firſt offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhal ſuffer like puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t penaltie, and forfeyture, as is conteyned in this acte againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal offendours for their firſt offence, and none other, And that the counſellours, procurers, comforters, &amp; abbettoures, for his or their ſecond offence ſhall ſuſteyne lyke punyſhment, penaltie, &amp; forfeyture as is conteined in this act agaynſt the principal offendour or offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doures for their ſecond offence, and none other.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ An acte for the puniſhment of brynging in of counterfeyte coyne of forrayne realmes, beynge curraunte wythin this realme. The .xi. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here diuerſe and ſondrye coynes of golde and ſiluer of other realmes, not beynge of the propre coyne of thys realme of Englande, and yet by the ſufferaunce and conſent of the kyng and quene our Soueraigne Lord and Lady, be curraunt in paiment within this realme, many yl diſpoſed perſons for their owne cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupte lucre &amp; aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage, haue now of late brought into this realme, from the parties of beyonde the ſea, greate quantitie of forged and counterfayte mony, lyke to the ſaid coine of other forreyne realmes, and haue vttered the ſame here by marchaundiſing, and otherwyſe to diuerſe of the ſubiectes of this realme, to their greate deceyt hurt and dammage, becauſe the ſayde yl diſpoſed perſones haue percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and vnderſtanded, that there was not, nor yet is any ſufficiente lawe or ſtatute made or prouided for the condigne puniſhment of the offendours in that behalfe.</p>
               <p>Wherefore be it enacted and eſtabliſhed by the aucthoritie of this preſent Parliament, that yf any perſon or perſones, after the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye daye of Ianuary next commynge, ſhal bryng from the partyes
<pb facs="tcp:25971:29"/>
of beyonde the ſea into this realme, or into any the dominions of the ſame any ſuch falſe and counterfeyte coyne or money, beyng currau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t within this realme as is aforeſayde, knowyng the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oine or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to be falſe and counterfeite, to thintent to vtter, or make paime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with the ſame within this realme, or any the dominions of the ſame, by marchaundiſyng, or otherwyſe, that all and euery ſuche perſon or perſones ſo offendyng, as is aforeſayde, their counſaylours, procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, aydours, and abbettours in that be halfe ſhalbe demed &amp; iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged to be offendours in high treaſon, and ſhall ſuffer after lawefull conuiction or attaynder thereof, ſuch paines of death, loſſe and forfai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture of landes, goodes, and cattelles, as other offendoures ſhal do, in caſes of high treaſon.</p>
               <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayd, that al, &amp; euery perſon and perſons, that ſhall at any tyme after the ſayde .xx. day of Ianuary, be accuſed or impeched of any of the offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and prouided for in this eſtatute, or of any other offence or offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, concernyng the impayrynge, counterfeyting, or forgyng of any coyne curraunte within this realme, ſhall and maye be endicted, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reyned, tryed, conuicted, or attaynted by ſuche like euidence, and in ſuch maner and fourme as hath bene vſed &amp; accuſtomed within this realme, at any time before the fyrſt yeare of the raygne of our late ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueraygne lorde kyng Edwarde the ſixt. Any ſtatute, cuſtome lawe, or vſage to the contrary thereof in any wyſe notwithſtanding.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ An acte for the impounding of diſtreſſes. The .xii. Chapyter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the auoydyng of greuous vexations, exactions, troubles, and diſorder in taking of diſtreſſes, and im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poundynge of cattel, be it enacted by aucthoritye of this preſent Parliament, that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; after the firſt dai of Apryl next co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, no diſtreſſe of cattel ſhalbe dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred, rape, wapentake, or lath, where ſuch dyſtreſſes is, or ſhalbe take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, except it be to a pounde, ouertwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſayd ſhire, not aboue thre myles diſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, from the place where the ſayde dyſtreſſe is taken, &amp; that no cattell, or other goods diſtrei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or taken by way of diſtreſſe, for any maner of cauſe: at one tyme ſhalbe impou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in ſeueral places, whereby the owner or owners of ſuch dyſtreſſe ſhalbe conſtrayned to ſue ſeuerall repleuis for the deli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uery of the ſayde diſtreſſe, ſo taken at one time, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> payne euery per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon offendyng contrary to this act, ſhal forfeyte to the party greued for euery ſuch offence a hundred ſhyllynges, and treble damages.</p>
               <p>And further be it enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayde, that after
<pb n="xxix" facs="tcp:25971:29"/>
the ſaid firſt day of Apryl, no perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or perſones ſhall take for kepin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> inpounde, imponndyng, or pondage of any maner of diſtreſſe, abou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſomme of .iiii. pence for any one whole diſtreſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhalbe ſo impou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded, and where leſſe hath bene vſed, there to take leſſe, vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> payne of fyne pounde to be payd to the party greued, ouer &amp; beſydes ſuche mony as he ſhall take, aboue the ſome of foure pence. Anye vſage or preſcription to the contrary in any wyſe notwithſtandyng.</p>
               <p>And for the more ſpedier deliuery of cattell, taken by waye of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, it is further enacted by the ſayd aucthoritie, that euery Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe of ſhires, being no cities nor townes made ſhyres, ſhall at his firſt countie day, or within two monethis nexte after he hath recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued his patent of his office o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhirifwike, ſhall depute, appoint &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clayme in the ſhyre towne within his baylyweke, foure deputies at the leaſt, dwellyng not aboue twelue myles, one dyſtaunt from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which ſayd deputies ſo appoynted &amp; proclamed, ſhall haue auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie in the ſheriffes name to make repleuies, and deliueraunce of ſuch diſtreſſes, in ſuch maner &amp; four me, as the ſheriffe, mai or ought to do, vpon paine that euery Sheriffe, for euery moneth that he ſhal lacke ſuch deputie, or deputies, ſhall forfeyte for euerye ſuche offence fyue poundes, the one halfe of whych forfaytures ſhalbe to the king &amp; Quenes highnes, her heires and ſucceſſours, the other halfe to him that wyll ſue for the ſame by byll, playnt, information, or action of debt, in any the kynge and quenes courtes of recorde, in which no eſſoygne protection, nor wager of lawe ſhalbe admitted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ An Acte appointing in order to iuſtices of peace touching the baylment of priſoners. ¶ The .xiii. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in the parliament holden at Weſtminſter, in the. iii yeare of the reigne of the noble prynce, king Henrye the ſeuenth, it was among other thinges ordeyned &amp; ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that no priſoner arreſted for felony, ſhould be lette<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to bayle or mainepryce, by any one Iuſtice of peace, but by the hole Iuſtices, or at leaſt by two of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whereof one to be of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Querum,</hi> Since the making of which eſtatute, one Iuſtice of peace, in the name of hym ſelfe and one other of the Iuſtices his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pagnion not makyng the ſayd Iuſtice partie nor priuie vnto the caſe, where fore the priſoner ſhould be bayled, hath often tymes by ſiniſter labor and meanes, ſet at large the greateſt, and notableſt offenders, ſuch as be not repleuiſable by the lawes of this realme, &amp; yet the rather to hyde their affections in that behalfe haue ſignified the cauſe of theyr apprehenſion to be put onely for ſuſpition of felony, wherby y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25971:30"/>
ſayd offendours hath eſcaped vnpunyſhed, and do dayly, to the high diſpleaſure of almightie God, the greate peril of the kyng and Que<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes true ſubiectes, and encoragement of all theues and euill doers.</p>
               <p>For reformation wherof, be it ordeined and enacted by the king and Quenes maieſties, the lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and the commons in this preſent parliament aſſembled, &amp; by aucthoritie of the ſame, that from, and after the fyrſt day of Apryll next commyng no Iuſtice or Iuſtices of peace, ſhall let to baile or mainepryce anye ſuch perſon or perſones, whych for any offence or offences, by them or any of them committed, be declared not to be repleuiſed or bailed or be forbidden to be repl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ued, or bailed, by the eſtatute of Weſtmin. prymer, made in the parliamente holden in the thyrde yeare of the reygne of kyng Edwarde the firſt. And furthermore, that any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſones arreſted for manſlaughter or felony, or ſuſpectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of manſlaughter or felony, beyng bayleable by the lawe, ſhal not after the ſayd fyrſt day of Apryll, be lette to bayle or maynepriſe, by anye Iuſtices of peace, if it be not in ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Seſſions, except it be bi two Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtices of peace, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt, wherof one to be of the <hi>Quorum,</hi> &amp; the ſame iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtices to be preſent together, at the tyme of the ſaid bailme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or main pryce, which hailement or mainprice they ſhall certifie in writynge, ſubſcribed, or ſygned with their owne handes, at the next generall goale deliuery, to be holden within the countie, where the ſayd per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon or perſon ſhalbe arreſted or ſuſpected. And that the ſayde Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices, or one of them being of the <hi>Quorum,</hi> when any ſuch priſoner is brought before them, for any manſlaughter or felonye, before anye baylement or maynepryce, ſhall take the examination of the ſaid pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoner, and information of them that brynges him, of the facte, &amp; cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtaunces thereof, &amp; the ſame, or aſmuch therof, as ſhal be materi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>all to proue the felonye, ſhall put in wrytynge before they make the ſame bailement, whiche ſayd examination together, with the ſayde baylement, the ſayd Iuſtices ſhall certifie at the next general goale delyuery to be holden within the lymittes of theyr commiſſion, and that euery Coroner, vpon any inquiſition before hym found, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by any perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or perſons ſhalbe in dicte for murther, or ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlaughter or as acceſſary or acceſſaries to the ſame, before the murder or man ſlaughter committed, ſhal put in wrytyng the effect of the euidence geuen to the Iurye before him, beyng materiall, and aſwell the ſaid Iuſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, as the ſayd Coroner, ſhal haue aucthoritie by this acte, to bind al ſuch bi recogniſaunce, or obligation, as do declare any thing material, to proue the ſaid murder or manſlaughter, offences, or fel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lonies, or to be acceſſary, or acceſſaries to the ſame, as is aforeſaid to appeare at the next general goall deliuery, to be holden within the Countie, citie, or towne corporat, wher the triall therof ſhalbe, then and ther to geue euidence againſt the partie ſo indicted at the tyme
<pb n="xxx" facs="tcp:25971:30"/>
of his triall, &amp; ſhall certifye aſwell the ſame euydence, as ſuche bonde and bondes in wryting, as he ſhal take together with the inquiſition or indictment before him taken and founde, at, or before the tyme, of his ſayd tryall therof, to be had or made. And lykewyſe, the ſayd Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices ſhall certifye all and euery ſuche bonde, taken before theym, in lyke maner as before is ſayd of baylementes and examination. And in caſe any Iuſtice of peace, or <hi>Quorum,</hi> or Coroner, ſhall after the ſayde fyrſt day of Apryll, offende in any thing contrary to the true intente, and meaning of this preſent acte: That then the Iuſtices of gaole de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyuery, of the Shire, citie, towne, or place, where ſuche offence ſhall happen to be committed, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> due profe therof, by examination before them ſhall for euery ſuch offence, ſet ſuche fyne on euerye of the ſame Iuſtices of peace, and Coroner, as the ſame Iuſtices o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gaole deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhall thynke me te, and ſhall eſtrete the ſame as other fynes and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merciamentes aſſeſſed before Iuſtices of gaole deliuery ought to be.</p>
               <p>Prouided alwaies, and be it further enacted by thauctoritye afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd, that Iuſtices of peace, &amp; Coroners within the cytye of London and the countye of Middelſex, and in other cities, boroughes, &amp; tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes corporat wythin this realme and Wales, ſhall within their ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall iuriſdictions, haue auctorytye to let to bayle, fellons and priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, in ſuch maner and forme, as they haue bene heretofore accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, thys act or any thinge therein conteyned, to the contrarye not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandyng. And alſo ſhal take examinations and bondes, as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayd, vpon euerye baylement by them or any of them to be made, and ſhal certifie euery ſuch baylementes, bondes, and examinations, by them or any of them, taken or made at the next gaole deliuerye to be holden within the ſhyre, citie, borough, or towne, where their ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral iuriſdictions extendeth, vpon like payne and forfeyture, as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore limitted in thys preſent act.</p>
               <p>And be it alſo enacted by the auctorytye aforeſayd, that no writers of <hi>Habeas cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us,</hi> or <hi>Certiorary,</hi> ſhalbe hereafter graunted to remoue anye pryſoner out of any gaole, or to remoue anye recogniſaunce, excepte the ſame writtes be ſygned with the proper handes of the chiefe Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, or in his abſence, one of the Iuſtices of the court, out of whyche the ſame writtes ſhalbe awarded, or made, vppon payne that he that writeth anye ſuche writtes, not beyng ſigned as is aforeſayde, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayt to our ſayd ſoueraygne lord the kyng and the queene, for euerye ſuch writte and writtes fiue poundes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ An act for the makyng of ruſſel ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, and fuſtian of Naples in Norwiche. ¶ The .xiiii. Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25971:31"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here of late yeres paſſed ruſſels, called ruſſels ſatte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and ſattens reuerſes, haue bene practiſed to be made beyonde the ſeas of the wolles bredde in the county of Norfolke, and by reaſon therof ſo great quanty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye of the ſayde ruſſelles ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, haue ben brought into this realme, ſolde &amp; worne aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel in euery part of this realme, as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> partes beyonde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeas that thereby the myſteries of worſtedes makynge and weuynge, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by marchauntes and inhabitauntes of the citye of Norwiche, haue heretofore ben wel maynteyned and relieued, is now at this preſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lmoſt wholy decayed and brought out of eſtimation, and verye lyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e worne, either within this realme, or in any other forreyne realms to the great hynderance, and decay of the ſayde cytye, and Citezens of the ſame citye. For remedy wherof Thomas Marſham, Maiour o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the citie of Norwiche Iohn Corbet Eſquier, Auſten Stewarde, Robert Leche, Robert Rugge, Iohn Ball, and Alexander Mather Aldermen of the ſayd citie. Thomas Whal, Thomas Pecke, Raphe Marſham, Robert Henry, Iohn Sutton, Rycharde Tomſon, Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tezins and marchauntes of the ſayd citye, at their great coſtes and charges, aſwel in brynging of certayn ſtrangers from the partes be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yonde the ſeas into the ſayd citie as alſo in makyng of Lombes, and all other prouiſion for the ſame, and alſo haue called vnto them eight perſons of the moſt diſcrete and worthy men of the miſterye of Wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtede weuyng, within the ſayd citie, that is to ſaye, Iohn Cooke, Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes Lyn, Iohn Croſſe, Simo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it, Iohn Marſhal, Roger L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cke Edmond Barker, and Edmonde Selers, beynge the number of .xxi perſons, which haue not only made Ruſſels Sattens, and Sattens <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>euerſes, and fuſtian o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Naples within the ſaid citie of Norwich of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wolles, but alſo haue learned &amp; taughte other citezins and in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>auntes of the ſaid citie to make the ſame, in ſuch good and per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fect maner, that much better Ruſſels Sattens, Sattens reuerſes, and fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Naples, and ſuch lyke, and for eaſier prices, be now at this preſent wrought and made within the ſayd citie, then hertofore hath ben, or nowe be made in anye of the parties beyonde the ſeas, whereby the ſaid citie and inhabitauntes therof maye, and be lyke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to be relieued and broughte to the olde eſtate, to the greate ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uauncement of the commodities of this realme, and enrichynge the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame, yf ſome good and polityke lawes and ordinaunces were made fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the good continuaunce of the true makynge of the ſayde Ruſſels Sattens, Sattens Reuerſes, and Fuſtian of Naples, and ſuche lyke.</p>
               <p>In conſideration whereof be it enacted by the aſſent of the kynge and quenes hyghnes, the Lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and the commons of this preſent Parliament aſſembled, and by thauctorytie
<pb n="xxx" facs="tcp:25971:31"/>
of the ſame, that the ſaide ruſſels ſattens, and ſattens reuerſes, &amp; fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian of Naples hereafter to be made only wythin the ſayd city, may from henceforth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the name, and be called by the name of Norwi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſattens and Norwich fuſtians, and that the maior and the afore mencioned citezens of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame citie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which before thys tyme hath ben at the coſtes and charges of the bringyng of the ſayd ſtrangers into the ſame city, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> makyng of the ſayd ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes and fuſtians of Naples, and ſuch the afore mencioned eyght per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons, that they haue called vnto them ſhalbe a felowſhyp of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfes and ſhal yerely the thyrd daye of February chooſe of theyr felowes, foure wardens within the guilde hall of the ſayd citie, or anye other common and conuenient place in the ſame cytye, and the ſame war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens ſo beynge chooſen, ſhall ſtande and be wardens of the ſame fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhyp duryng one whole yeare, next enſuing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid election &amp; that the ſame wardeynes after the ſayd election ſhal come before the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior of the ſayd city for the tyme being, yerely the mondaye next after the ſaide thyrde daye of February, and before the ſayde maior ſhalbe ſworne diligently to viewe ſearch, and ſee al the ruſſels ſattens, ſat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens reuerſes, and fuſtian of Naples, then made or that ſhalbe made within the ſayd citie, duryng the ſayd yeare. And ſuche of the ſayde ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, &amp; fuſtian of Naples, as ſhal apeare and be demed by them to be lawfully truely &amp; workmanly wrought ſhal ſeale with a ſeale of leade, bearing the armes of the citie of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiche, wherby it may be knowen to the marchaunt or buyer of them that the ſame be allowed and truly made.</p>
               <p>And that alſo it may be enacted by the auctorytye aforeſayd, that the ſayd wardens and felowſhyp ſhalbe a bodye corporate, and to be named and be enabled by this act to ſue, and be ſued and to geue, and to take by the name of wardeynes and felowſhyppe of the myſterye of ruſſel ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, and fuſtian of Norwiche makyng within the ſayd citye of Norwiche. And yf any defaulte at any tyme ſhalbe founde in any of the ſayd ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes &amp; fu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian of Norwich, or in any of them by the ſayd wardeynes, that the ſame default ſhalbe reformed and the offendour or offendours ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to be puniſhed according to ſuch rules and ordinaunces, as hereaf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter from time to tyme ſhalbe made within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd city by the maior of the ſayd city for the tyme beyng, and by the ſayde foure wardeynes, and the felowſhyp of the ſayde occupation or myſterye, or the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt number of the ſayd felowſhyppe for, and concernynge the ſame, and that the ſame defaultes from time to time, as occaſion ſhal ſerue ſhalbe enquired of, &amp; tried before the maior of the ſayd cytye of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiche for the time beynge, by the othes of twelue honeſte menne of the foreſayde felowſhyppe. And that the ſayde foure wardeynes ſo choſen and ſworne, ſhal haue full power &amp; auctorytye, to doo execute,
<pb facs="tcp:25971:32"/>
preſent, and reforme all and ſinguler thyng and thinges, of, for, and concernyng the ſayd myſterie, makyng workyng and occupiynge of the ſaid ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſers &amp; fuſtian of Norwich with in the ſayde citie in ſuch maner and forme as in or by the ſayde ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances ſhalbe expreſſed and declared, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t al tymes hereafter and from time to time it ſhal lawfull to the Maior of the ſayde cytye for the tyme beyng, and to the before named felowſhyp &amp; wardeynes of the ſame myſterie, and the more part of them, &amp; to their ſucceſſors, to make and ordeyne from time to time rules, lawes &amp; ordinaunces mete and neceſſary for the good order and gouernance of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, and for the true and wel makyng of the ſayd ruſſels ſattens, ſat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tens reuerſes, and fuſtian of Norwiche, and the ſame ordinances ſo made to be at al tymes obeyed by al thin habitaunce of the ſaid city, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uburbes of the ſame &amp; to be put in due execution by the ſaid maior &amp; wardeyns, and their ſucceſſors for the time beyng in ſuch maner and forme as by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayde ordinaunce ſhalbe ordeyned and declared. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſuch as now be and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hereafter ſhalbe makers of the ſaid ruſſels ſat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens, ſattens reuerſes, &amp; fuſtian of Norwich, &amp; euery of them within the ſayd city ſhal not from hence forth occupy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayde myſterie &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the ſaid ruſſels ſatte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſattens reuerſes, &amp; fuſtyan of Norwi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, nor any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> within the ſayde city by them ſelues, or by anye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, before he or they ſo occupying the ſayd myſtery within the ſayd citie be made free of the ſayd citie, and admitted to be of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip by the maior of the ſayde citie, &amp; wardeyns and felowſhyp of the ſaid myſterye for the tyme beyng. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no perſon do occupy by him ſelfe or any other for him out of the ſayd city, the ſayd myſterie of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kyng of ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, &amp; fuſtians of Naples or of any of them, before he or they ſo occupiyng the ſame, haue ben pre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tice to the ſaid myſterie by the terme of ſeuen yeares, or els admitted by the ſayde maior and felowſhyp or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more part of them, vpon payne of forfeyture of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ruſſels ſatte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſattens reuerſes, &amp; fuſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be made co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the forme of this act.</p>
               <p>Prouided alwaies &amp; be it enacted by thauctoritye aforeſayde, that the ſayd maior and wardeyns for the tyme beyng ſhal not take anye ſumme of money, or reward to their owne proper vſes for the admit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting of any perſon or perſons, to occupy the ſaid myſtery vpon paine of forfeyture of treble the value of the reward or ſumme of money ſo by them or any of them to be taken.</p>
               <p>Prouided alſo, that it ſhalbe lawfull to the ſayde wardeynes, and to euery of them for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time being, by al wayes and meanes &amp; at al law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful times, dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly from time to time, to make ſearch by dewe &amp; ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary waies, for al maner of the ſaid ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes and fuſtian of Norwiche, that ſhal happen to be found by them defec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, for lacke of good and true workma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſhyp. And that it ſhalbe law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="xxxii" facs="tcp:25971:32"/>
to the ſayd wardeynes &amp; euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the time being by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of this acte, to ſeaſe &amp; take the ſayd ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and fuſtian, &amp; bringe and preſent the ſame clothes ſo ſeaſed &amp; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, to the Maior of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid citie for the time being, &amp; vnto his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to thintent that twelue honeſt, lawful, and expert men of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid myſterie, &amp; felowſhip being ſworne before the ſaid Maior, mai by ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue of their othes, make inquirie, and preſent the maner of the ſayde defaultes before the ſaid Maior, for the time being according to ſuch good and holſom ordinances and rules, as ſhalbe ordeined and made for the conſeruation &amp; good continuance of the ſaide occupation and miſterie, &amp; the true makyng and working of the ſaid ruſſels ſattens, ſattens, reuerſes, &amp; fuſtians of Norwiche. And that al &amp; euery perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and perſons, that ſhall occupy, vſe, &amp; exerciſe the ſaid miſterie, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the ſaid ruſſels ſattens, ſatte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s reuerſes, &amp; fuſtians of Norwi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, or any of them, contrary to the forme, tenour, playne meaning<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; intent of this act, and of the rules and ordinaunces, that at any time hereafter by auctoritie of this acte ſhalbe ordeyned &amp; made for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuaunce of the true &amp; perfect making of the ſaid ruſſels ſattens, ſat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tens reuerſes &amp; fuſtian of Norwiche, ſhal forfeyte and loſe for euerye tyme ſo offending, or making any ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, &amp; fuſtian of Norwiche, contrarie to the meaning, tenour &amp; effect of the ſaid acte, rules, and ordinaunces, concerning the ſame, ſuche fines, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merciamentes, &amp; paines as ſhalbe adiudged, aſſeſſed, and affered by twelue experte men of the ſaid felowſhip vpon their othes, the ſame twelue perſons to be ſworne before the ſaid Maior &amp; wardeynes to enquire and make true verdict, &amp; preſentment of ſuch defaultes, the one half of al which forfeyture to be to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maior of the ſaid citie for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time being, &amp; his ſucceſſors, and thother moitie to the ſaid wardeins for the tyme being, &amp; ther ſuccſſours, by action of dette, bil playnt, or informatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in any courte of record, in which action, bil, plaint or infor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mation no wager of lawe, protection, inuencio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or forren Ple, ſhalbe allowed. And in caſe it ſhal fortune hereafter, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any of the ſaid ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, &amp; fuſtian of Norwich ſhal lacke of ſuch leng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thes &amp; bredes, or of the true &amp; enſuing making or ſorting of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yarne as ſhalbe appointed, &amp; ſet furth by the ſayd rules &amp; ordinaunces, and the ſame ſo to be found defectiue by verdict of twelue men of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd feloſhyp before the ſayd Maior &amp; wardeins &amp; their ſucceſſors: That the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſaid ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, &amp; fuſtians of Naples, &amp; euery of them ſo found defectiue, to be cutte in two peeces, &amp; to paye ſuch fine or fines as ſhalbe offered &amp; affered by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaide twelue expert men by vertue of their othes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one moitie of which fine or fines to be to the Maior of the ſayd citie for the tyme being, &amp; to his ſucceſſours, and thother moytie to the wardeynes of the ſayd felowſhype for the tyme beyng, and to their ſuccceſſours.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25971:33"/>
Prouided alwaies and be it further enacted by thauctoritie afore ſayd, that if any wardeyne or wardeines for the time beyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid myſt erie or occupation of making ruſſels ſattens, ſat tens reuerſes, &amp; ſuſtian of Naples, ſhal at any time hereafter ſeale, or cauſe to be ſea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led any ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, or fuſtians of Naples, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhal not be wel ſufficient and truely wrought, and made according to the true entent and meanyng of thys preſent act, ſhal forfeyt &amp; looſe for euery pece ſo ſealed, being not wel ſufficient and truly wrought and made, the whole value of euery ſuch pece ſo ſealed, thone half of whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che forfeytures to be to the kyng and Quenes maieſties, her heyres and ſucceſſors, and thother moyte therof to be to ſuch perſon &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as ſhal ſue for the ſame by byll, action, or information, in anye of the kynges courtes of record, in whiche byl, action, or information no eſſoygne protection, or wager of lawe ſhalbe allowed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ An act to confirme the liberties of the lorde Marchers in Wales. ¶ The .xv. Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Umbly beſechen your excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t maieſties, your true &amp; faythful Subiectes, the lord Marchers bothe ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and temporal, within your highnes dominion of Wales, that wher as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> parliament holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Weſt. the .xxvii. yere of the raygne of kyng Henry theyght father vnto you our natural Soueraygne ladye, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt other thinges one acte was made &amp; eſtabliſhed for lawes &amp; iuſtice to be miniſtred in the ſayd dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Wales, in lyke forme as it is in this realme of England, in the whiche acte one article is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for that the lords Marchers before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> parliament had vſed to put their tenauntes wythin the lordſhips Marchers, vnder common mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryce &amp; ſuerty of apparaunce, and haue had the forfeytures thereof, which for euer from &amp; after the feaſt of al ſainctes then next enſuinge the ſayd parliament ſhould vtterlye ſeaſe, &amp; be determined. It was enacted that after the ſaid feaſt of al ſaynctes, euery lay &amp; temporall perſon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beyng alord Marcher, ſhould haue the moyte or halfe of euery forfeiture of al and euery common mainprice, recogniſance for the peace or apparance, forfeited by any of their tenantes inhabiting within any of their lordſhips marchers, &amp; they to be payed the ſame moytie or halfe by the handes of the ſhyreffe of euery of the counties where ſuch for feyture ſhalbe, yf the ſhyriff can leuie the ſame, and the ſame ſhyriffe to accompt to our ſayd late ſoueraygne lord the kynge for the other half or moytie, in ſuch excheker as thei can be acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tant. And further it was enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayde, that all and euery lay, &amp; temporal perſon or perſons, then being lords marchers and hauing any lordſhips marchers, or lordſhyps royal ſhould from and after the ſayd feaſt of al ſayntes, haue al ſuch myſes and profites
<pb n="xxxii" facs="tcp:25971:33"/>
of their tenantes, as thei haue had or vſed to haue at the firſt entrye into theyr landes in tymes paſt. And alſo ſhould haue hold &amp; kepe, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the precinct of their lordſhippes, courtes Baron, courtes lete, and lawdayes, and al and euery thing to the ſaid courtes belonging, and alſo ſhuld haue within the precinct of their ſaid lordſhyps, or lawday wayf, ſtrayf, infangthefe, outfangthefe, treaſure trouie, deodandes, goodes &amp; cattels of fellons, and of perſons co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempned or outlawed of fellony or murther, put in exigent for fellony or murther, and alſo wrecke de mer, wharfage, and cuſtomes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtraungers, as thei haue haue had in tyme paſt, as though ſuch priuileges graunted vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by poynt of charter, any thing in that acte to the contrary notwyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd act of parliament more at large it may apeare.</p>
               <p>And for aſmuch as biſhops, and other eccleſiaſtical perſons beynge lordes marche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, hauing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like liberties, caſualties, profyttes, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>modities, within their lordſhips marchers, &amp; lordſhyps royal, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſayd dominion, or principalitie of Wales, wer not prouided for by the expreſſe letter of the ſayde ſtatute, in lyke ſort as the laye and temporal lordes marchers were, but rather of purpoſe as it ſhoulde ſeme forgotten and left out of the ſayde acte, agaynſt all reaſon, and good equitie: And foraſmuch alſo, as the heyres and ſucceſſors of the lay &amp; temporallordes marchers, then being were not prouided for, by the limitation and expreſſe wordes of the ſayd act, aſwel as theyr aunceſters &amp; predeceſſors were, as reaſon wold thei ſhuld haue ben.</p>
               <p>It may pleaſe your maieſties of your moſt gracious fauoure and benignitie at the humble ſuit and ſupplication of your ſayd faythfull ſubiectes the lordes marchers that now are, in the ſayd dominion of Wales, both ſpiritual &amp; temporal, to graunt that it maye by thaſſent of the lords ſpiritual and temporal, and the commons in this preſent parliament aſſembled, be ordeyned, eſtabliſhed, and enacted, by thaue torytye of thys preſent parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that aſwel your ſaid ſpiritual &amp; ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical ſubiectes, lordes marchers, nowe hauinge lordſhips mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, or lordſhips royal in Wales aforeſayde, &amp; theyr ſucceſſors, and the ſucceſſours of euery of them, as alſo the heyres and ſucceſſours of the lordes temporal marchers, that then were or nowe be, and the heyres or ſucceſſours of euery of them being, or which hereafter ſhal be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ordes marchers within their lordſhips marchers, and lordſhyps royal in the dominion or principalitie of Wales, ſhal haue and enioye to them &amp; to their heires &amp; ſucceſſors, reſpectiuely and ſeuerally for euer the moytie &amp; half of euery forfeyture, of al &amp; euery co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>price recogniſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for the pea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e or apparance forfeyted by anye theyr tena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes inhabiting w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in any of their lordſhips marchers, or lordſhips royal. &amp; they to be payd the ſame moytie or halfe by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> handes of the ſhyriffe of the countie, for the time beyng, after ſuche forme &amp; ſor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> as the ſayd lay or temporal lords marchers haue bene or ought to haue
<pb facs="tcp:25971:34"/>
bene payed the ſame, by force of the ſayde Sta tute.</p>
               <p>And further, ſhal haue all ſuch miſes, &amp; profites of their tenan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, as the lords marchers, ſpiritual or temporal, reſpectiuely, or ſeuerallye had or vſed to haue at theyr fyrſt entry into their la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des in tymes paſt before the making of the ſaid act or ſtatute. And alſo ſhal haue, hold, &amp; kepe within the precinct of their ſaid lordſhips, al ſuch courtes baron courtes lete, &amp; lawdayes, &amp; al and euery thing and thinges, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame courtes belonging, &amp; alſo ſhal haue within the precincte of theyr ſayd ſeuerall lordſhips, or lawdayes, al ſuche waif, ſtrayf, infang thefe, out fang thefe, treaſure trouis, deodandes, goodes, &amp; cattels offellons, &amp; of perſons condempned or outlawed of fellony or murther, put in exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent for fellony or murther, and alſo al ſuch wrecke demer, wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fage, and cuſtomes of ſtraungers, as the lordes Marchers, ſpirituall and temporal, reſpectiuely, and ſeuerally had &amp; vſed in tymes paſt, before the makyng of the ſayd ſtatute.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ An act for the continuaunce of certayne ſtatutes. Cap. xvi.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Her in the parliament begon &amp; holden at London the .iij. daye of Nouember, in the .xxi. yeare of the raygne of oure moſt dread ſoueraigne lord of moſt famous memory, king Henry theyght, &amp; from thence adiourned to Weſtm. and there holden &amp; continued by diuers prorogations, vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſſolution therof, one act was made and eſtabliſhed for the reſtrainte of cariage, &amp; conueynge of horſes, &amp; mares out of this realme, &amp; alſo one other acte was there made for the true windinge of wolles, and one other act was there made, to reſtraine killyng of wailinges, bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lockes, ſtieres, &amp; heyfers, being vnder thage of .ii. yeres which ſayde ſeueral actes were then made to endure &amp; continue to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> next parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid ſeueral actes more playnly appeareth. And wher alſo in the ſayd parliament, one other act was made &amp; eſtabliſhed for attaintes to be ſued for the puniſhment of periury, vpon vntrue ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dites, which actes laſt before reherſeb, were then made &amp; ordeyned, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue &amp; endure to the laſt day of the next parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t as by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame act more playnly at large is ſhewed &amp; may apeare. And wher alſo in the parliament begon &amp; holden at Weſtm. theyght day of Iune, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> xxviii. yere of the raygne of our ſayd moſt drad ſoueraigne lord king Henry the .viii. &amp; ther continued &amp; kepte vnto the diſſolution therof <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t was ordeyned &amp; enacted, that al &amp; ſinguler the ſaid actes aboue re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>membred, &amp; euery of them, ſhould continue &amp; endure in their force &amp; ſtrength, &amp; alſo be obſerued &amp; kept vntyl the laſt day of the next par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, as by the ſame act amonges other things therin conteyned more playnly appeareth. And where alſo in the parliament begon &amp; holden at Weſt. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> xxviii. day of Apryl in the .xxxi. yere of the raygne of our ſaydlate moſt dread ſoueraigne lord kyng Henry the eyght, &amp;
<pb n="xxxiiii" facs="tcp:25971:34"/>
there continued vntyll the, xxviii, day of Iune then next folowing, it was ordeined and enacted by thauctoritie of the ſame parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> al &amp; ſinguler the ſaid ſeueral actes aboue remembred &amp; euery of them &amp; al clauſes, articles, &amp; prouiſions in them, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uery of them contayned, ſhould continue &amp; endure in their force &amp; ſtrength, &amp; alſo be obſerued &amp; kept vntill the laſt day of the next parliament, as by the ſame act a monges other thinges therin contained, more playnelye appeareth. And where in the parliament holden at Weſtm. in the .xxxv. yeare of the reigne of our ſayd late ſoueraygne lorde kynge Henry theight, one act was made for the preſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of woods, to endure for. vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, yeares then next folowing, &amp; from thence to thend of the next parliament, as by the ſame act more playnely doth &amp; may appeare. And wher alſo at the parliament holden at Weſt. in the .xxxvii. yeare of the reigne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd king Henry theight, &amp; ther continued and kept vntil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thereof it was ordeined &amp; enacted y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> al &amp; ſinguler the ſaid actes aboue mentioned, &amp; euery of them excepte the ſaid act made for the preſerua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of wodes, as is aforeſaid, ſhuld continue &amp; eudure in their force &amp; ſtrength, &amp; alſo to be obſerued &amp; kept, vntil the laſt day of the next par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liament then folowyng, as by the ſame act amongs other things ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in conteined more playnely appeareth. And where alſo at the ſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the parliament, ended at Weſt. in the .xiiii. day of March, in the third yeare of the reygne of our ſoueraygne Lord kyng Edwarde the .vi. one acte was made for the true currying of leather, whyche act was made to endure to thend of the next parliament, as by the ſame acte more playnely appeareth. And where alſo at the ſeſſyon of a Parlya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ended at at Weſt. the firſt day of February, in the fourthe yeare of the reigne of our ſayd lateſoueraygne Lord king Edwarde the. vi one act was then &amp; there made, concerning the buying of ro ther bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes. And alſo one other act was then &amp; there made touchyng the bui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; ſell of butter &amp; cheſe, whych ſayd ſeuerall actes, were then and there made, to endure &amp; continue, to the ende of the next parliament as by the ſame ſeuerall actes more at large it doth and may appeare. And where alſo at the ſeſſion of a parliament by prorogation holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Weſt. the, xxiii, day of Ianuary in the .v. year of the reigne of our ſaid ſouer aygne lord, one other act was then and there made, agaynſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratours and forſtallers to endure to thend of the nexte parlyament, which al &amp; ſinguler the ſayd actes aboue mentioned together, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid act concerning the preſeruation of wodes, at a parliament holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Weſtm. the fyrſt day of March, in the .vii. yeare of the raygne of our ſaid ſoueraygne Lord kyng Edwarde the .vi. &amp; there continued and dyſſolued the laſt day of the ſame moneth of March, &amp; all clauſes articles &amp; prouyſions in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; euery of them conteined were there re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiued &amp; continued, to ſtand in their force &amp; ſtrength, vntil the laſt day of the next parliament. And where alſo at the ſeſſion of a parliament holden by prorogatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Weſt. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xxiiii day of October, in the .i. yeare
<pb facs="tcp:25971:35"/>
of the raygne of our moſt gratious ſoueraygne lady y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quene, &amp; there continued &amp; kept vntil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſſolution therof, one acte was ther made &amp; eſtabliſhed agaynſt vnlawful &amp; rebellious aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bles, to endure to thend of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> next parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t as by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame act more plainli doth &amp; may appeare. And wher alſo at the ſame ſeſſion of parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, laſt before mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ed, al &amp; ſinguler the actes aboue mentioned &amp; before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time continued at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dri parliamentes, as is aforeſayd, &amp; clauſes, articles, and prouiſions in them and euery of them conteyned, wer ther reuiued, &amp; continued to ſtand in their force &amp; ſtrength, vnto the laſt daye of the next parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Foraſmuche as al and ſinguler the ſaid ſeueral actes aboue mentioned be good &amp; beneficial for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth of this realme Be it therfore enacted ordeined &amp; eſtabliſhed by the king &amp; quene our ſoueraign lord &amp; lady with thaſſent of the lordes ſpiritual &amp; temporal &amp; the commons in this preſent parliamente aſſembled &amp; by thauctoritie of the ſame y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> al &amp; ſinguler the ſayd ſeuerall actes and eſtatutes aboue mentioned &amp; rehearſed, &amp; euery of them and al clauſes articles, &amp; prouiſions in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; euery of them co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teined, ſhalbe reuiued, continued, ſtand &amp; endure in theyr force &amp; ſtrength, to al intentes, conſtructions, &amp; purpoſes &amp; ſhal be obſerued &amp; kept in al thinges, vntil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt day of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> next parliament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ An act touchyng leaſes hereafter to be made by certayne ſpiritual perſones. Cap .xvii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in the parliament begon &amp; holden at Weſt. the eight day of Iune, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xxviii. year of the raygne of our late king of famous memory Henry theight, &amp; there co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued &amp; kept vntil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſſolution of the ſame parliament, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xviii. dai of Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne next folowyng, one act intituled, an act for reſtitution of the fyrſte fruites in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me of vacation, to the next incu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bent, was had &amp; made, wherin are certaine clauſes for leaſes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made, &amp; to be made bi ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tual &amp; eccleſiaſtical perſons, to endure, &amp; be in force for terme of, vi. ye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ares if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> incumbentes did reſigne ther ſayd ſpiritual promotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſhould otherwiſe becom void by thonli act of the ſame thincu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, ys by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame act more at large may appeare. To thintent the per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſones and vycares and others, hauing cure ofſoules, mai y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better at<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tende, and be the more vigilaunt in their miſtery and function.</p>
               <p>Be it enacted by the king our ſoueraygne lord, &amp; the quene our ſoue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raygne lady with thaſſentes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes ſpiritual &amp; temporal &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mons in this preſent parliament aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled &amp; by thauctoritie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> aſmuch of the ſame acte, as doth concerne the making good of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid leaſes ne any clauſe, ſentente, prouiſion, or article therein conteyned ſhal extend, or be conſtrued, or adiudged to extende to anye leaſe, that ſhalbe made by any perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vicar or any other hauing any ſpiritual pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>motion, after the feaſt of the purificication of our Lady next co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Excuſum Londini in aedibus Iohannis Cawodi, Tipographi Regiae Maiestatis</hi> Anno MDLV.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25971:35"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
